<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter n="1" name="Enjoyment In Untroubled Ease">
    <section n="1" type="parable">
        <p>In the Northern Ocean there is a fish, the name of which is Kun - I do not know how many
            li in size. It changes into a bird with the name of Peng, the back of which is (also) -
            I do not know how many li in extent. When this bird rouses itself and flies, its wings
            are like clouds all round the sky. When the sea is moved (so as to bear it along), it
            prepares to remove to the Southern Ocean. The Southern Ocean is the Pool of Heaven.</p>
        <p><ref kind="historical">There is the (book called) Qi Xie, a record of marvels. We have in it these words: 'When
            the peng is removing to the Southern Ocean it flaps (its wings) on the water for 3000
            li. Then it ascends on a whirlwind 90,000 li, and it rests only at the end of six
            months.'</ref> (But similar to this is the movement of the breezes which we call) the horses
            of the fields, of the dust (which quivers in the sunbeams), and of living things as they
            are blown against one another by the air.<rhetorical>Is its azure the proper colour of the sky?</rhetorical> Or
            is it occasioned by its distance and illimitable extent? If one were looking down (from
            above), the very same appearance would just meet his view.</p>
        <p> And moreover, (to speak of) the accumulation of water; if it be not great, it will not
            have strength to support a large boat. Upset a cup of water in a cavity, and a straw
            will float on it as if it were a boat. Place a cup in it, and it will stick fast; the
            water is shallow and the boat is large. (So it is with) the accumulation of wind; if it
            be not great, it will not have strength to support great wings. Therefore (the peng
            ascended to) the height of 90,000 li, and there was such a mass of wind beneath it;
            thenceforth the accumulation of wind was sufficient. As it seemed to bear the blue sky
            on its back, and there was nothing to obstruct or arrest its course, it could pursue its
            way to the South.</p>
        <p>A cicada and a little dove laughed at it, saying, <speech speaker="Cicada and Dove">'We
                make an effort and fly towards an elm or sapanwood tree; and sometimes before we
                reach it, we can do no more but drop to the ground. Of what use is it for this
                (creature) to rise 90,000 li, and make for the South?'</speech> He who goes to the
            grassy suburbs, returning to the third meal (of the day), will have his belly as full as
            when he set out; he who goes to a distance of 100 li will have to pound his grain where
            he stops for the night; he who goes a thousand li, will have to carry with him
            provisions for three months. What should these two small creatures know about the
            matter? <comparison topic="knowledge">The knowledge of that which is small does not reach to that which is great; (the
            experience of) a few years does not reach to that of many.</comparison> <rhetorical>How do we know that it is so?</rhetorical>
            The mushroom of a morning does not know (what takes place between) the beginning and end
            of a month; the short-lived cicada does not know (what takes place between) the spring
            and autumn. These are instances of a short term of life. In the south of <ref kind="geographic">Chu</ref> there is
            the (tree) called Ming-ling, whose spring is 500 years, and its autumn the same; in high
            antiquity there was that called Da-chun, whose spring was 8000 years, and its autumn the
            same. And Peng Zu is the one man renowned to the present day for his length of life: <rhetorical>if
            all men were (to wish) to match him, would they not be miserable?</rhetorical></p>
    </section>
    <section n="2" type="argument">
        <p>In the questions put by Tang to Ji we have similar statements:<speech speaker="Tang">'In
                the bare and barren north there is the dark and vast ocean - the Pool of Heaven. In
                it there is a fish, several thousand li in breadth, while no one knows its length.
                Its name is the kun. There is (also) a bird named the peng; its back is like the Tai
                mountain, while its wings are like clouds all round the sky. <figurative style="simile">On a whirlwind it
                mounts upwards as on the whorls of a goat's horn</figurative> for 90,000 li, till, far removed
                from the cloudy vapours, <figurative style="symbolism">it bears on its back the blue sky</figurative>, and then it shapes its
                course for the South, and proceeds to the ocean there.' A quail by the side of a
                marsh laughed at it, and said, 'Where is it going to? I spring up with a bound, and
                come down again when I have reached but a few fathoms, and then fly about among the
                brushwood and bushes; and this is the perfection of flying. Where is that creature
                going to?</speech>' This shows the difference between the small and the great.</p>
    </section>
    <section n="3" type="argument">
        <p>Thus it is that men, whose wisdom is sufficient for the duties of some one office, or
            whose conduct will secure harmony in some one district, or whose virtue is befitting a
            ruler so that they could efficiently govern some one state, are sure to look on
            themselves in this manner (like the quail), and yet Rongzi of Song would have smiled and
            laughed at them. (This Rongzi), <figurative style="hyperbole">though the whole world should have praised him</figurative>, would
            not for that have stimulated himself to greater endeavour, and <figurative style="hyperbole">though the whole world
            should have condemned him</figurative>, would not have exercised any more repression of his course;
            so fixed was he in the difference between the internal (judgment of himself) and the
            external (judgment of others), so distinctly had he marked out the bounding limit of
            glory and disgrace. Here, however, he stopped. <figurative style="personification">His place in the world indeed had become
            indifferent to him</figurative>, but still he had not planted himself firmly (in the right position).
            There was Liezi, who rode on the wind and pursued his way, with an admirable
            indifference (to all external things), returning, however, after fifteen days, (to his
            place). In regard to the things that (are supposed to) contribute to happiness, he was
            free from all endeavours to obtain them; but though he had not to walk, there was still
            something for which he had to wait. But suppose one who mounts on (the ether of) heaven
            and earth in its normal operation, and drives along the six elemental energies of the
            changing (seasons), thus enjoying himself in the illimitable - what has he to wait for?
            Therefore it is said, 'The Perfect man has no (thought of) self; the Spirit-like man,
            none of merit; the Sagely-minded man, none of fame.' </p>
    </section>
    <section n="4" type="parable">
        <p> Yao, proposing to resign the throne to Xu You, said, <speech speaker="Yao">'When the sun
                and moon have come forth, if the torches have not been put out, would it not be
                difficult for them to give light? When the seasonal rains are coming down, if we
                still keep watering the ground, will not our toil be labour lost for all the good it
                will do? Do you, Master, stand forth (as sovereign), and the kingdom will (at once)
                be well governed. If I still (continue to) preside over it, I must look on myself as
                vainly occupying the place - I beg to resign the throne to you.'</speech> Xu You
            said, <speech speaker="Xu You">'You, Sir, govern the kingdom, and the kingdom is well
                governed. If I in these circumstances take your place, shall I not be doing so for
                the sake of the name? But the name is but the guest of the reality; shall I be
                playing the part of the guest? The tailor-bird makes its nest in the deep forest,
                but only uses a single branch; the mole drinks from the He, but only takes what
                fills its belly. Return and rest in being ruler - I will have nothing to do with the
                throne. Though the cook were not attending to his kitchen, the representative of the
                dead and the officer of prayer would not leave their cups and stands to take his
                place.'</speech></p>
    </section>
    <section n="5" type="parable">
        <p>Jian Wu asked Lian Shu, saying, <speech speaker="Jian Wu">'I heard Jie Yu talking words
                which were great, but had nothing corresponding to them (in reality); once gone,
                they could not be brought back. I was frightened by them; they were like the Milky
                Way which cannot be traced to its beginning or end. They had no connexion with one
                another, and were not akin to the experiences of men.'</speech>
            <speech speaker="Lian Shu">'What were his words?'</speech> asked Lian Shu, and the other
            replied, (He said) that<speech speaker="Jian Wu"> 'Far away on the hill of Gu Ye there
                dwelt a Spirit-like <figurative style="simile">man whose flesh and skin were (smooth) as ice and (white) as
                snow</figurative>; that his <figurative style="simile">manner was elegant and delicate as that of a virgin;</figurative> that he did not
                eat any of the five grains, but inhaled the wind and drank the dew; that he mounted
                on the clouds, drove along the flying dragons, rambling and enjoying himself beyond
                the four seas; that by the concentration of his spirit-like powers he could save men
                from disease and pestilence, and secure every year a plentiful harvest.'</speech>
            These words appeared to me wild and incoherent and I did not believe them. <speech
                speaker="Lian Shu">'So it is,'</speech> said Lian Shu. <speech speaker="Lian Shu"
                >'The blind have no perception of the beauty of elegant figures, nor the deaf of the
                sound of bells and drums. But is it only the bodily senses of which deafness and
                blindness can be predicated? There is also a similar defect in the intelligence; and
                of this your words supply an illustration in yourself. That man, with those
                attributes, though all things were one mass of confusion, and he heard in that
                condition the whole world crying out to him to be rectified, would not have to
                address himself laboriously to the task, as if it were his business to rectify the
                world. Nothing could hurt that man; the greatest floods, reaching to the sky, could
                not drown him, nor would he feel the fervour of the greatest heats melting metals
                and stones till they flowed, and scorching all the ground and hills. From the dust
                and chaff of himself, he could still mould and fashion Yaos and Shuns - <rhetorical topic="purpose">how should
                he be willing to occupy himself with things?</rhetorical>'</speech> A man of Song, who dealt in
            the ceremonial caps (of Yin), went with them to Yue, the people of which cut off their
            hair and tattooed their bodies, so that they had no use for them. Yao ruled the people
            of the kingdom, and maintained a perfect government within the four seas. Having gone to
            see the four (Perfect) Ones on the distant hill of Gu Ye, when (he returned to his
            capital) on the south of the Fen water, his throne appeared no more to his deep-sunk
            oblivious eyes.</p>
    </section>
    <section n="6" type="argument">
        <p>Huizi told Zhuangzi, saying,<speech speaker="Huizi">'The king of Wei sent me some seeds
                of a large calabash, which I sowed. The fruit, when fully grown, could contain five
                piculs (of anything). I used it to contain water, but it was so heavy that I could
                not lift it by myself. I cut it in two to make the parts into drinking vessels; but
                the dried shells were too wide and unstable and would not hold (the liquor); nothing
                but large useless things! Because of their uselessness I knocked them to
                pieces.'</speech> Zhuangzi replied, <speech speaker="Zhuangzi">'You were indeed
                stupid, my master, in the use of what was large. There was a man of Song who was
                skilful at making a salve which kept the hands from getting chapped; and (his
                family) for generations had made the bleaching of cocoon-silk their business. A
                stranger heard of it, and proposed to buy the art of the preparation for a hundred
                ounces of silver. The kindred all came together, and considered the proposal. "We
                have," said they, "been bleaching cocoon-silk for generations, and have only gained
                a little money. Now in one morning we can sell to this man our art for a hundred
                ounces - let him have it." The stranger accordingly got it and went away with it to
                give counsel to the king of Wu, who was then engaged in hostilities with Yue. The
                king gave him the command of his fleet, and in the winter he had an engagement with
                that of Yue, on which he inflicted a great defeat, and was invested with a portion
                of territory taken from Yue. The keeping the hands from getting chapped was the same
                in both cases; but in the one case it led to the investiture (of the possessor of
                the salve), and in the other it had only enabled its owners to continue their
                bleaching. The difference of result was owing to the different use made of the art.
                Now you, Sir, had calabashes large enough to hold five piculs; why did you not think
                of making large bottle-gourds of them, by means of which you could have floated over
                rivers and lakes, instead of giving yourself the sorrow of finding that they were
                useless for holding anything. Your mind, my master, would seem to have been closed
                against all intelligence!'</speech></p>
    </section>
    <section n="7" type="parable">
        <p>Huizi said to Zhuangzi, <speech speaker="Huizi">'I have a large tree, which men call the
                Ailantus. Its trunk swells out to a large size, but is not fit for a carpenter to
                apply his line to it; its smaller branches are knotted and crooked, so that the disk
                and square cannot be used on them. Though planted on the wayside, a builder would
                not turn his head to look at it. Now your words, Sir, are great, but of no use - all
                unite in putting them away from them.'</speech> Zhuangzi replied, <speech
                speaker="Zhuangzi">'Have you never seen a wildcat or a weasel? There it lies,
                crouching and low, till the wanderer approaches; east and west it leaps about,
                avoiding neither what is high nor what is low, till it is caught in a trap, or dies
                in a net. Again there is the Yak, <figurative style="simile">so large that it is like a cloud hanging in the
                sky</figurative>. It is large indeed, but it cannot catch mice. You, Sir, have a large tree and
                are troubled because it is of no use - why do you not plant it in a tract where
                there is nothing else, or in a wide and barren wild? There you might saunter idly by
                its side, or in the enjoyment of untroubled ease sleep beneath it. Neither bill nor
                axe would shorten its existence; there would be nothing to injure it. <rhetorical topic="purpose">What is there
                in its uselessness to cause you distress?</rhetorical></speech>'</p>
    </section>
</chapter>
