<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="repo/Zhuangzi-and-taoism/schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapters>
    <chapter n="1" name="Enjoyment In Untroubled Ease">
        <section n="1" type="parable">
            <p>In the Northern Ocean there is a fish, the name of which is Kun - I do not know how
                many li in size. It changes into a bird with the name of Peng, the back of which is
                (also) - I do not know how many li in extent. When this bird rouses itself and
                flies, its wings are like clouds all round the sky. When the sea is moved (so as to
                bear it along), it prepares to remove to the Southern Ocean. The Southern Ocean is
                the Pool of Heaven.</p>
            <p><ref kind="historical">There is the (book called) Qi Xie, a record of marvels. We
                    have in it these words: 'When the peng is removing to the Southern Ocean it
                    flaps (its wings) on the water for 3000 li. Then it ascends on a whirlwind
                    90,000 li, and it rests only at the end of six months.'</ref> (But similar to
                this is the movement of the breezes which we call) the horses of the fields, of the
                dust (which quivers in the sunbeams), and of living things as they are blown against
                one another by the air.<rhetorical>Is its azure the proper colour of the
                    sky?</rhetorical> Or is it occasioned by its distance and illimitable extent? If
                one were looking down (from above), the very same appearance would just meet his
                view.</p>
            <p> And moreover, (to speak of) the accumulation of water; if it be not great, it will
                not have strength to support a large boat. Upset a cup of water in a cavity, and a
                straw will float on it as if it were a boat. Place a cup in it, and it will stick
                fast; the water is shallow and the boat is large. (So it is with) the accumulation
                of wind; if it be not great, it will not have strength to support great wings.
                Therefore (the peng ascended to) the height of 90,000 li, and there was such a mass
                of wind beneath it; thenceforth the accumulation of wind was sufficient. As it
                seemed to bear the blue sky on its back, and there was nothing to obstruct or arrest
                its course, it could pursue its way to the South.</p>
            <p>A cicada and a little dove laughed at it, saying, <speech speaker="Cicada and Dove"
                    >'We make an effort and fly towards an elm or sapanwood tree; and sometimes
                    before we reach it, we can do no more but drop to the ground. Of what use is it
                    for this (creature) to rise 90,000 li, and make for the South?'</speech> He who
                goes to the grassy suburbs, returning to the third meal (of the day), will have his
                belly as full as when he set out; he who goes to a distance of 100 li will have to
                pound his grain where he stops for the night; he who goes a thousand li, will have
                to carry with him provisions for three months. What should these two small creatures
                know about the matter? <comparison topic="knowledge">The knowledge of that which is
                    small does not reach to that which is great; (the experience of) a few years
                    does not reach to that of many.</comparison>
                <rhetorical>How do we know that it is so?</rhetorical> The mushroom of a morning
                does not know (what takes place between) the beginning and end of a month; the
                short-lived cicada does not know (what takes place between) the spring and autumn.
                These are instances of a short term of life. In the south of <ref kind="geographic"
                    >Chu</ref> there is the (tree) called Ming-ling, whose spring is 500 years, and
                its autumn the same; in high antiquity there was that called Da-chun, whose spring
                was 8000 years, and its autumn the same. And Peng Zu is the one man renowned to the
                present day for his length of life: <rhetorical>if all men were (to wish) to match
                    him, would they not be miserable?</rhetorical></p>
        </section>
        <section n="2" type="argument">
            <p>In the questions put by Tang to Ji we have similar statements:<speech speaker="Tang"
                    >'In the bare and barren north there is the dark and vast ocean - the Pool of
                    Heaven. In it there is a fish, several thousand li in breadth, while no one
                    knows its length. Its name is the kun. There is (also) a bird named the peng;
                    its back is like the Tai mountain, while its wings are like clouds all round the
                    sky. <figurative style="simile">On a whirlwind it mounts upwards as on the
                        whorls of a goat's horn</figurative> for 90,000 li, till, far removed from
                    the cloudy vapours, <figurative style="symbolism">it bears on its back the blue
                        sky</figurative>, and then it shapes its course for the South, and proceeds
                    to the ocean there.' A quail by the side of a marsh laughed at it, and said,
                    'Where is it going to? I spring up with a bound, and come down again when I have
                    reached but a few fathoms, and then fly about among the brushwood and bushes;
                    and this is the perfection of flying. Where is that creature going to?</speech>'
                This shows the difference between the small and the great.</p>
        </section>
        <section n="3" type="argument">
            <p>Thus it is that men, whose wisdom is sufficient for the duties of some one office, or
                whose conduct will secure harmony in some one district, or whose virtue is befitting
                a ruler so that they could efficiently govern some one state, are sure to look on
                themselves in this manner (like the quail), and yet Rongzi of Song would have smiled
                and laughed at them. (This Rongzi), <figurative style="hyperbole">though the whole
                    world should have praised him</figurative>, would not for that have stimulated
                himself to greater endeavour, and <figurative style="hyperbole">though the whole
                    world should have condemned him</figurative>, would not have exercised any more
                repression of his course; so fixed was he in the difference between the internal
                (judgment of himself) and the external (judgment of others), so distinctly had he
                marked out the bounding limit of glory and disgrace. Here, however, he stopped.
                    <figurative style="personification">His place in the world indeed had become
                    indifferent to him</figurative>, but still he had not planted himself firmly (in
                the right position). There was Liezi, who rode on the wind and pursued his way, with
                an admirable indifference (to all external things), returning, however, after
                fifteen days, (to his place). In regard to the things that (are supposed to)
                contribute to happiness, he was free from all endeavours to obtain them; but though
                he had not to walk, there was still something for which he had to wait. But suppose
                one who mounts on (the ether of) heaven and earth in its normal operation, and
                drives along the six elemental energies of the changing (seasons), thus enjoying
                himself in the illimitable - what has he to wait for? Therefore it is said, 'The
                Perfect man has no (thought of) self; the Spirit-like man, none of merit; the
                Sagely-minded man, none of fame.' </p>
        </section>
        <section n="4" type="parable">
            <p> Yao, proposing to resign the throne to Xu You, said, <speech speaker="Yao">'When the
                    sun and moon have come forth, if the torches have not been put out, would it not
                    be difficult for them to give light? When the seasonal rains are coming down, if
                    we still keep watering the ground, will not our toil be labour lost for all the
                    good it will do? Do you, Master, stand forth (as sovereign), and the kingdom
                    will (at once) be well governed. If I still (continue to) preside over it, I
                    must look on myself as vainly occupying the place - I beg to resign the throne
                    to you.'</speech> Xu You said, <speech speaker="Xu You">'You, Sir, govern the
                    kingdom, and the kingdom is well governed. If I in these circumstances take your
                    place, shall I not be doing so for the sake of the name? But the name is but the
                    guest of the reality; shall I be playing the part of the guest? The tailor-bird
                    makes its nest in the deep forest, but only uses a single branch; the mole
                    drinks from the He, but only takes what fills its belly. Return and rest in
                    being ruler - I will have nothing to do with the throne. Though the cook were
                    not attending to his kitchen, the representative of the dead and the officer of
                    prayer would not leave their cups and stands to take his place.'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="5" type="parable">
            <p>Jian Wu asked Lian Shu, saying, <speech speaker="Jian Wu">'I heard Jie Yu talking
                    words which were great, but had nothing corresponding to them (in reality); once
                    gone, they could not be brought back. I was frightened by them; they were like
                    the Milky Way which cannot be traced to its beginning or end. They had no
                    connexion with one another, and were not akin to the experiences of
                    men.'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Lian Shu">'What were his words?'</speech> asked Lian Shu, and the
                other replied, (He said) that<speech speaker="Jian Wu"> 'Far away on the hill of Gu
                    Ye there dwelt a Spirit-like <figurative style="simile">man whose flesh and skin
                        were (smooth) as ice and (white) as snow</figurative>; that his <figurative
                        style="simile">manner was elegant and delicate as that of a
                        virgin;</figurative> that he did not eat any of the five grains, but inhaled
                    the wind and drank the dew; that he mounted on the clouds, drove along the
                    flying dragons, rambling and enjoying himself beyond the four seas; that by the
                    concentration of his spirit-like powers he could save men from disease and
                    pestilence, and secure every year a plentiful harvest.'</speech> These words
                appeared to me wild and incoherent and I did not believe them. <speech
                    speaker="Lian Shu">'So it is,'</speech> said Lian Shu. <speech
                    speaker="Lian Shu">'The blind have no perception of the beauty of elegant
                    figures, nor the deaf of the sound of bells and drums. But is it only the bodily
                    senses of which deafness and blindness can be predicated? There is also a
                    similar defect in the intelligence; and of this your words supply an
                    illustration in yourself. That man, with those attributes, though all things
                    were one mass of confusion, and he heard in that condition the whole world
                    crying out to him to be rectified, would not have to address himself laboriously
                    to the task, as if it were his business to rectify the world. Nothing could hurt
                    that man; the greatest floods, reaching to the sky, could not drown him, nor
                    would he feel the fervour of the greatest heats melting metals and stones till
                    they flowed, and scorching all the ground and hills. From the dust and chaff of
                    himself, he could still mould and fashion Yaos and Shuns - <rhetorical
                        topic="purpose">how should he be willing to occupy himself with
                        things?</rhetorical>'</speech> A man of Song, who dealt in the ceremonial
                caps (of Yin), went with them to Yue, the people of which cut off their hair and
                tattooed their bodies, so that they had no use for them. Yao ruled the people of the
                kingdom, and maintained a perfect government within the four seas. Having gone to
                see the four (Perfect) Ones on the distant hill of Gu Ye, when (he returned to his
                capital) on the south of the Fen water, his throne appeared no more to his deep-sunk
                oblivious eyes.</p>
        </section>
        <section n="6" type="argument">
            <p>Huizi told Zhuangzi, saying,<speech speaker="Huizi">'The king of Wei sent me some
                    seeds of a large calabash, which I sowed. The fruit, when fully grown, could
                    contain five piculs (of anything). I used it to contain water, but it was so
                    heavy that I could not lift it by myself. I cut it in two to make the parts into
                    drinking vessels; but the dried shells were too wide and unstable and would not
                    hold (the liquor); nothing but large useless things! Because of their
                    uselessness I knocked them to pieces.'</speech> Zhuangzi replied, <speech
                    speaker="Zhuangzi">'You were indeed stupid, my master, in the use of what was
                    large. There was a man of Song who was skilful at making a salve which kept the
                    hands from getting chapped; and (his family) for generations had made the
                    bleaching of cocoon-silk their business. A stranger heard of it, and proposed to
                    buy the art of the preparation for a hundred ounces of silver. The kindred all
                    came together, and considered the proposal. "We have," said they, "been
                    bleaching cocoon-silk for generations, and have only gained a little money. Now
                    in one morning we can sell to this man our art for a hundred ounces - let him
                    have it." The stranger accordingly got it and went away with it to give counsel
                    to the king of Wu, who was then engaged in hostilities with Yue. The king gave
                    him the command of his fleet, and in the winter he had an engagement with that
                    of Yue, on which he inflicted a great defeat, and was invested with a portion of
                    territory taken from Yue. The keeping the hands from getting chapped was the
                    same in both cases; but in the one case it led to the investiture (of the
                    possessor of the salve), and in the other it had only enabled its owners to
                    continue their bleaching. The difference of result was owing to the different
                    use made of the art. Now you, Sir, had calabashes large enough to hold five
                    piculs; why did you not think of making large bottle-gourds of them, by means of
                    which you could have floated over rivers and lakes, instead of giving yourself
                    the sorrow of finding that they were useless for holding anything. Your mind, my
                    master, would seem to have been closed against all intelligence!'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="7" type="parable">
            <p>Huizi said to Zhuangzi, <speech speaker="Huizi">'I have a large tree, which men call
                    the Ailantus. Its trunk swells out to a large size, but is not fit for a
                    carpenter to apply his line to it; its smaller branches are knotted and crooked,
                    so that the disk and square cannot be used on them. Though planted on the
                    wayside, a builder would not turn his head to look at it. Now your words, Sir,
                    are great, but of no use - all unite in putting them away from them.'</speech>
                Zhuangzi replied, <speech speaker="Zhuangzi">'Have you never seen a wildcat or a
                    weasel? There it lies, crouching and low, till the wanderer approaches; east and
                    west it leaps about, avoiding neither what is high nor what is low, till it is
                    caught in a trap, or dies in a net. Again there is the Yak, <figurative
                        style="simile">so large that it is like a cloud hanging in the
                        sky</figurative>. It is large indeed, but it cannot catch mice. You, Sir,
                    have a large tree and are troubled because it is of no use - why do you not
                    plant it in a tract where there is nothing else, or in a wide and barren wild?
                    There you might saunter idly by its side, or in the enjoyment of untroubled ease
                    sleep beneath it. Neither bill nor axe would shorten its existence; there would
                    be nothing to injure it. <rhetorical topic="purpose">What is there in its
                        uselessness to cause you distress?</rhetorical></speech>'</p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter n="2" name="The Adjustment of Controversies">
        <section n="1" type="parable">
            <p>Nan-Guo Zi-Qi was seated, leaning forward on his stool. He was looking up to heaven
                and breathed gently, seeming to be in a trance, and to have lost all consciousness
                of any companion. (His disciple), Yan Cheng Zi-You, who was in attendance and
                standing before him, said, <speech speaker="Yan Cheng Zi-You">'What is this?
                        <rhetorical topic="body and soul">Can the body be made to become thus like a
                        withered tree, and the mind to become like slaked lime?</rhetorical>His
                    appearance as he leans forward on the stool to-day is such as I never saw him
                    have before in the same position.'</speech> Zi-Qi said, <speech
                    speaker="Nan-Guo Zi-Qi">'Yan, you do well to ask such a question, I had just now
                    lost myself; but how should you understand it?<comparison topic="heaven">You may
                        have heard the notes of Man, but have not heard those of Earth; you may have
                        heard the notes of Earth, but have not heard those of
                    Heaven.'</comparison></speech></p>
            <p>Zi-You said, <speech speaker="Yan Cheng Zi-You">'I venture to ask from you a
                    description of all these.'</speech> The reply was, <speech
                    speaker="Nan-Guo Zi-Qi">'When the breath of the Great Mass (of nature) comes
                    strongly, it is called Wind. <rhetorical>Sometimes it does not come so; but when
                        it does, then from a myriad apertures there issues its excited noise; have
                        you not heard it in a prolonged gale? Take the projecting bluff of a
                        mountain forest - in the great trees, a hundred spans
                        round,</rhetorical><figurative style="metaphor">the apertures and cavities
                        are like the nostrils, or the mouth, or the ears; now square, now round like
                        a cup or a mortar; here like a wet footprint, and there like a large puddle.
                        (The sounds issuing from them are like) those of fretted water, of the
                        arrowy whizz,of the stern command, of the inhaling of the breath, of the
                        shout, of the gruff note, of the deep wail, of the sad and piping
                        note.</figurative> The first notes are slight, and those that follow deeper,
                    but in harmony with them. <comparison>Gentle winds produce a small response;
                        violent winds a great one. When the fierce gusts have passed away, all the
                        apertures are empty (and still)</comparison> have you not seen this in the
                    bending and quivering of the branches and leaves?'</speech></p>
            <p>Zi-You said, <speech speaker="Yan Cheng Zi-You">'<comparison>The notes of Earth then
                        are simply those which come from its myriad apertures; and the notes of Man
                        may just be compared to those which (are brought from the tubes of) bamboo-
                        allow me to ask about the notes of Heaven.'</comparison></speech> Zi-Qi
                replied, <speech speaker="Nan-Guo Zi-Qi"><rhetorical>'Blowing the myriad
                        differences, making them stop [proceed] of themselves, sealing their
                        self-selecting - who is it that stirs it all up?'</rhetorical></speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="2" type="argument">
            <p><comparison topic="knowledge">Great knowledge is wide and comprehensive; small
                    knowledge is partial and restricted. Great speech is exact and complete; small
                    speech is (merely) so much talk.</comparison><comparison topic="body and soul"
                    >When we sleep, the soul communicates with (what is external to us); when we
                    awake, the body is set free. </comparison> Our intercourse with others then
                leads to various activity, and daily there is the striving of mind with
                    mind.<negative>There are hesitancies; deep difficulties; reservations; small
                    apprehensions causing restless distress, and great apprehensions producing
                    endless fears.</negative><figurative style="metaphor" topic="right and wrong"
                    >Where their utterances are like arrows from a bow, we have those who feel it
                    their charge to pronounce what is right and what is wrong; where they are given
                    out like the conditions of a covenant, we have those who maintain their views,
                    determined to overcome.</figurative>
                <figurative style="metaphor">(The weakness of their sections), like the decay (of
                    things) in autumn and winter, shows the failing (of the minds of some) from day
                    to day;or it is like their water which, once voided, cannot be gathered up
                    again.</figurative>
                <comparison>Then their ideas seem as if fast bound with cords, showing that the mind
                    is become like an old and dry moat, and that it is nigh to death, and cannot be
                    restored to vigour and brightness. ThenJoy and anger, sadness and pleasure,
                    anticipation and regret, fickleness and fixedness, vehemence and indolence,
                    eagerness and tardiness;</comparison>-- <figurative style="metaphor">(all these
                    moods), like music from an empty tube, or mushrooms from the warm moisture,day
                    and night succeed to one another and come before us, and we do not know whence
                    they sprout.</figurative> Let us stop! Let us stop! <rhetorical>Can we expect to
                    find out suddenly how they are produced?</rhetorical></p>
        </section>
        <section n="3" type="argument">
            <p><paradox>If there were not (the views of) another, I should not have mine; if there
                    were not I (with my views), his would be uncalled for:-- this is nearly a true
                    statement of the case, but we do not know what it is that makes it be
                    so.</paradox><figurative style="metaphor" topic="the true one">It might seem as
                    if there would be a true Governor concerned in it, but we do not find any trace
                    (of his presence and acting). That such an One could act so I believe; but we do
                    not see His form. He has affections, but He has no form.<rhetorical><figurative
                            style="metaphor">Given the body, with its hundred parts, its nine
                            openings, and its six viscera, all complete in their places, which do I
                            love the most?</figurative> Do you love them all equally? or do you love
                        some more than others? Is it not the case that they all perform the part of
                        your servants and waiting women? All of them being such, are they not
                        incompetent to rule one another? or do they take it in turns to be now ruler
                        and now servants?</rhetorical></figurative>
                <paradox>There must be a true Ruler (among them) whether by searching you can find
                    out His character or not, there is neither advantage nor hurt, so far as the
                    truth of His operation is concerned.</paradox></p>
            <p> When once we have received the bodily form complete, its parts do not fail to
                perform their functions till the end comes.<rhetorical topic="body and soul">In
                    conflict with things or in harmony with them, they pursue their course to the
                    end, with the speed of a galloping horse which cannot be stopped - is it not
                    sad? To be constantly toiling all one's lifetime, without seeing the fruit of
                    one's labour, and to be weary and worn out with his labour, without knowing
                    where he is going to - is it not a deplorable case? Men may say, 'But it is not
                    death;' yet of what advantage is this? When the body is decomposed, the mind
                    will be the same along with it - must not the case be pronounced very
                    deplorable? Is the life of man indeed enveloped in such darkness? Is it I alone
                    to whom it appears so? And does it not appear to be so to other men?
                </rhetorical></p>
        </section>
        <section n="4" type="argument">
            <p><comparison topic="knowledge"><rhetorical>If we were to follow the judgments of the
                        predetermined mind, who would be left alone and without a
                        teacher?</rhetorical> Not only would it be so with those who know the
                    sequences (of knowledge and feeling) and make their own selection among them,
                    but it would be so as well with the stupid and unthinking. For one who has not
                    this determined mind, to have his affirmations and negations is like the case
                    described in the saying, 'He went to Yue to-day, and arrived at it
                    yesterday.'</comparison> It would be making what was not a fact to be a fact.
                But even <ref kind="historical">the spirit-like Yu</ref> could not have known how to
                do this, and how should one like me be able to do it? But speech is not like the
                blowing (of the wind); <rhetorical>the speech has (a meaning in) his words.If,
                    however, what he says, be indeterminate (as from a mind not made up), does he
                    then really speak or not? He thinks that his words are different from the
                    chirpings of fledgelings; but is there any distinction between them or not? But
                    how can the Dao be so obscured, that there should be 'a True' and 'a False' in
                    it? How can speech be so obscured that there should be 'the Right' and 'the
                    Wrong' about them? Where shall the Dao go to that it will not be found? Where
                    shall speech be found that it will be inappropriate?</rhetorical> Dao becomes
                obscured through the small comprehension (of the mind), and speech comes to be
                obscure through the vain-gloriousness (of the speech). So it is that we have the
                contentions between the <ref kind="historical">Literati and the Mohists</ref>, the
                one side affirming what the other denies, and vice versa. If we would decide on
                their several affirmations and denials, no plan is like bringing the (proper) light
                (of the mind) to bear on them.</p>
        </section>
        <section n="5" type="argument">
            <p><paradox>There is no thing that is not "that", and there is no thing that is not
                    "this". If I look at something from "that", I do not see it; only if I look at
                    it from knowing do I know it.</paradox> Hence it is said, 'That view comes from
                this; and this view is a consequence of that:' - which is the theory that that view
                and this (the opposite views) produce each the other. <comparison>Although it be so,
                    there is affirmed now life and now death; now death and now life; now the
                    admissibility of a thing and now its inadmissibility; now its inadmissibility
                    and now its admissibility.</comparison></p>
            <p><comparison topic="right and wrong">(The disputants) now affirm and now deny; now
                    deny and now affirm. Therefore the sagely man does not pursue this method, but
                    views things in the light of (his) Heaven (-ly nature), and hence forms his
                    judgment of what is right. This view is the same as that, and that view is the
                    same as this. But that view involves both a right and a wrong; and this view
                    involves also a right and a wrong</comparison> - <rhetorical>are there indeed
                    the two views, that and this? Or are there not the two views, that and
                    this?</rhetorical> They have not found their point of correspondency which is
                called the pivot of the Dao. As soon as one finds this pivot, he stands in the
                centre of the ring (of thought), where he can respond without end to the changing
                views; without end to those affirming, and without end to those denying. Therefore I
                said, 'There is nothing like the proper light (of the mind).'</p>
        </section>
        <section n="6" type="argument">
            <p><figurative style="symbolism">By means of a finger (of my own) to illustrate that the
                    finger (of another) is not a finger is not so good a plan as to illustrate that
                    it is not so by means of what is (acknowledged to be) not a finger; <ref
                        kind="historical">and by means of (what I call) a horse to illustrate that
                        (what another calls) a horse is not so, is not so good a plan as to
                        illustrate that it is not a horse, by means of what is (acknowledged to be)
                        not a horse.</ref> (All things in) heaven and earth may be (dealt with as) a
                    finger; (each of) their myriads may be (dealt with as) a horse.</figurative>
                Does a thing seem so to me? (I say that) it is so. Does it seem not so to me? (I say
                that) it is not so. A path is formed by (constant) treading on the ground. A thing
                is called by its speaker through the (constant) application of the speaker to it.
                    <paradox>How is it so? It is so because it is so. How is it not so? It is not
                    so, because it is not so.</paradox></p>
            <p> Everything has its inherent character and its proper capability. There is nothing
                which has not these. <comparison>Therefore, this being so,if we take a stalk of
                    grain and a (large) pillar, a loathsome (leper) and <ref kind="historical">(a
                        beauty like) Xi Shi</ref>, things large and things insecure, things crafty
                    and things strange;</comparison> they may in the light of the Dao all be reduced
                to the same category (of opinion about them). <paradox>It was separation that led to
                    completion; from completion ensued dissolution. But all things, without regard
                    to their completion and dissolution, may again be comprehended in their
                    unity</paradox> - it is only the far reaching in thought who know how to
                comprehend them in this unity. This being so, let us give up our devotion to our own
                views, and occupy ourselves with the ordinary views. These ordinary views are
                grounded on the use of things. (The study of that) use leads to the comprehensive
                judgment, and that judgment secures the success (of the inquiry). That success
                gained, we are near (to the object of our search), and there we stop. When we stop,
                and yet we do not know how it is so, we have what is called the Dao.</p>
            <p> When we toil our spirits and intelligence, obstinately determined (to establish our
                own view), and do not know the agreement (which underlies it and the views of
                others), we have what is called 'In the morning three.' What is meant by that 'In
                the morning three?' <ref kind="indirect-quote">A keeper of monkeys, in giving them
                    out their acorns, (once) said, 'In the morning I will give you three (measures)
                    and in the evening four.' This made them all angry, and he said, 'Very well. In
                    the morning I will give you four and in the evening three.' The monkeys were all
                    pleased. His two proposals were substantially the same, but the result of the
                    one was to make the creatures angry, and of the other to make them pleased</ref>
                - an illustration of the point I am insisting on. Therefore the sagely man brings
                together a dispute in its affirmations and denials, and rests in the equal
                fashioning of Heaven. Both sides of the question are admissible.</p>
        </section>
        <section n="7" type="argument">
            <p>Among the men of old their knowledge reached the extreme point.<rhetorical
                    topic="the true one">What was that extreme point? Some held that at first there
                    was not anything.</rhetorical>
                <comparison>This is the extreme point, the utmost point to which nothing can be
                    added. A second class held that there was something, but without any responsive
                    recognition of it (on the part of men). A third class held that there was such
                    recognition, but there had not begun to be any expression of different opinions
                    about it.</comparison> It was through the definite expression of different
                opinions about it that there ensued injury to (the doctrine of) the Dao. It was this
                injury to the (doctrine of the) Dao which led to the formation of (partial)
                    preferences.<figurative style="metaphor">Was it indeed after such preferences
                    were formed that the injury came? or did the injury precede the rise of such
                    preferences?If the injury arose after their formation, Zhao's method of playing
                    on the lute was natural. If the injury arose before their formation, there would
                    have been no such playing on the lute as Zhao's.</figurative>
                <ref kind="historical">Zhao Wen's playing on the lute</ref>, <ref kind="historical"
                    >Shi Kuang's indicating time with his staff</ref>, and <ref kind="historical"
                    >Huizi's (giving his views)</ref>,</p>
            <p>while leaning against a dryandra tree (were all extraordinary). <positive>The
                    knowledge of the three men (in their several arts) was nearly perfect, and
                    therefore they practised them to the end of their lives.</positive> They loved
                them because they were different from those of others.They loved them and wished to
                make them known to others. But as they could not be made clear, though they tried to
                make them so, they ended with the obscure (discussions) about <ref kind="historical"
                    >'the hard' and 'the white.'</ref>
                <negative>And their sons, moreover, with all the threads of their fathers'
                    compositions, yet to the end of their lives accomplished nothing.</negative>
                <comparison>If they, proceeding in this way, could be said to have succeeded, then
                    am I also successful; if they cannot be pronounced successful, neither I nor any
                    other can succeed.</comparison><figurative style="metaphor" topic="the true one"
                    >Therefore the scintillations of light from the midst of confusion and
                    perplexity are indeed valued by the sagely man; but not to use one's own views
                    and to take his position on the ordinary views is what is called using the
                    (proper) light.</figurative></p>
        </section>
        <section n="8" type="argument">
            <p>But here now are some other sayings -I do not know whether they are of the same
                character as those which I have already given, or of a different character. Whether
                they be of the same character or not when looked at along with them, they have a
                character of their own, which cannot be distinguished from the others. But though
                this be the case, let me try to explain myself. <paradox topic="existence">There was
                    a beginning. There was a beginning before that beginning. There was a beginning
                    previous to that beginning before there was the beginning. There was existence;
                    there had been no existence. There was no existence before the beginning of that
                    no existence. There was no existence previous to the no existence before there
                    was the beginning of the no existence. If suddenly there was nonexistence, we do
                    not know whether it was really anything existing, or really not
                    existing.</paradox> Now I have said what I have said, but I do not know whether
                what I have said be really anything to the point or not.</p>
        </section>
        <section n="9" type="argument">
            <p><comparison>under heaven there is nothing greater than the tip of an autumn down, and
                    the <ref kind="geographic">Tai mountain</ref> is
                    small.</comparison><comparison>There is no one more long-lived than a child
                    which dies prematurely, and <ref kind="geographic">Peng Zu</ref> did not live
                    out his time.</comparison><rhetorical topic="existence">Heaven, Earth, and I
                    were produced together, and all things and I are one. Since they are one, can
                    there be speech about them? But since they are spoken of as one, must there not
                    be room for speech? <figurative style="symbolism">One and Speech are two; two
                        and one are three.</figurative> Going on from this (in our enumeration), the
                    most skilful reckoner cannot reach (the end of the necessary numbers), and how
                    much less can ordinary people do so! Therefore from non-existence we proceed to
                    existence till we arrive at three; proceeding from existence to existence, to
                    how many should we reach? Let us abjure such procedure, and simply rest
                    here.</rhetorical></p>
        </section>
        <section n="10" type="argument">
            <p>The Dao at first met with no responsive recognition. Speech at first had no constant
                forms of expression. Because of this there came the demarcations (of different
                    views).<comparison>Let me describe those demarcations: they are the Left and the
                    Right; the Relations and their Obligations; Classifications and their
                    Distinctions; Emulations and Contentions. These are what are called 'the Eight
                    Qualities.'</comparison> Outside the limits of the world of men, the sage
                occupies his thoughts, but does not discuss about anything; inside those limits he
                occupies his thoughts, but does not pass any judgments. In the <ref
                    kind="historical">Chun Qiu</ref>, which embraces the history of the former
                kings, the sage indicates his judgments, but does not argue (in vindication of
                them). Thus it is that he separates his characters from one another without
                appearing to do so, and argues without the form of section. How does he do so? The
                sage cherishes his views in his own breast, while men generally state theirs
                sectionatively, to show them to others. Hence we have the saying, 'Disputation is a
                proof of not seeing clearly.<comparison topic="the true one">'The Great Dao does not
                    admit of being praised. The Great section does not require words. Great
                    Benevolence is not (officiously) benevolent. Great Disinterestedness does not
                    vaunt its humility. Great Courage is not seen in stubborn bravery. The Dao that
                    is displayed is not the Dao. Words that are sectionative do not reach the point.
                    Benevolence that is constantly exercised does not accomplish its object.
                    Disinterestedness that vaunts its purity is not genuine. Courage that is most
                    stubborn is ineffectual. These five seem to be round (and complete), but they
                    tend to become square (and immovable).</comparison></p>
            <p><rhetorical topic="knowledge">Therefore the knowledge that stops at what it does not
                    know is the greatest.</rhetorical> Who knows the section that needs no words,
                and the Way that is not to be trodden? He who is able to know this has what is
                called 'The Heavenly Treasure-house.' He may pour into it without its being filled;
                he may pour from it without its being exhausted; and all the while he does not know
                whence (the supply) comes. This is what is called 'The Store of Light.'Therefore of
                    <ref kind="historical">old Yao</ref> asked <ref kind="historical">Shun</ref>,
                saying, 'I wish to smite (the rulers of) <ref kind="historical">Zong</ref>, <ref
                    kind="historical">Kuai</ref>, and <ref kind="historical">Xu-Ao</ref>. Even when
                standing in my court, I cannot get them out of my mind. How is it so?' Shun replied,
                'Those three rulers live (in their little states) as if they were among the mugwort
                and other brushwood - how is it that you cannot get them out of your mind? Formerly,
                ten suns came out together, and all things were illuminated by them; how much should
                (your) virtue exceed (all) suns!'</p>
        </section>
        <section n="11" type="parable">
            <p>Nie Que asked Wang Ni, saying, <speech speaker="Nie Que">'Do you know, Sir, what all
                    creatures agree in approving and affirming?'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Wang Ni">'How should I know it?'</speech> was the reply. <speech
                    speaker="Nie Que">'Do you know what it is that you do not know?'</speech> asked
                the other again, and <speech speaker="Wang Ni">he got the same reply.</speech> He
                asked a third time, <speech speaker="Nie Que">'Then are all creatures thus without
                    knowledge?'</speech> and <speech speaker="Wang Ni">Wang Ni answered as
                    before</speech>, (adding however), <speech speaker="Wang Ni"
                        >'<paradox>Notwithstanding, I will try and explain my meaning. How do you
                        know that when I say "I know it," I really (am showing that) I do not know
                        it, and that when I say "I do not know it," I really am showing that I do
                        know it.'</paradox> And let me ask you some questions: '<comparison>If a man
                        sleep in a damp place, he will have a pain in his loins, and half his body
                        will be as if it were dead; but will it be so with an eel? If he be living
                        in a tree, he will be frightened and all in a tremble; but will it be so
                        with a monkey? And does any one of the three know his right place
                        ?</comparison>
                    <comparison>Men eat animals that have been fed on grain and grass; deer feed on
                        the thick-set grass; centipedes enjoy small snakes; owls and crows delight
                        in mice; but does any one of the four know the right taste?</comparison>
                    <comparison>The dog-headed monkey finds its mate in the female gibbon; the elk
                        and the axis deer cohabit; and the eel enjoys itself with other
                        fishes.</comparison>
                    <comparison><ref kind="historical">Mao Qiang</ref> and <ref kind="historical">Li
                            Ji</ref> were accounted by men to be most beautiful, but when fishes saw
                        them, they dived deep in the water from them; when birds, they flew from
                        them aloft; and when deer saw them, they separated and fled away.But did any
                        of these four know which in the world is the right female
                        attraction?</comparison> As I look at the matter, the first principles of
                    benevolence and righteousness and the paths of approval and disapproval are
                    inextricably mixed and confused together - how is it possible that I should know
                    how to discriminate among them?'</speech></p>
            <p>Nie Que said (further),<speech speaker="Nie Que"> 'Since you, Sir, do not know what
                    is advantageous and what is hurtful, is the Perfect man also in the same way
                    without the knowledge of them?'</speech> Wang Ni replied, <speech
                    speaker="Wang Ni">'<figurative style="hyperbole" topic="spirit-like man">The
                        Perfect man is spirit-like. Great lakes might be boiling about him, and he
                        would not feel their heat; <ref kind="geographic">the He</ref> and <ref
                            kind="geographic">the Han</ref> might be frozen up, and he would not
                        feel the cold; the hurrying thunderbolts might split the mountains, and the
                        wind shake the ocean, without being able to make him afraid. Being such, he
                        mounts on the clouds of the air, rides on the sun and moon, and rambles at
                        ease beyond the four seas. Neither death nor life makes any change in him,
                        and how much less should the considerations of advantage and injury do
                        so!'</figurative></speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="12" type="parable">
            <p>Qu Quezi asked Chang Wuzi, saying, <speech speaker="Qu Quezi">'I heard the Master
                    (speaking of such language as the following): "The sagely man does not occupy
                    himself with worldly affairs. He does not put himself in the way of what is
                    profitable, nor try to avoid what is hurtful; he has no pleasure in seeking (for
                    anything from any one); <paradox>he does not care to be found in (any
                        established) Way; he speaks without speaking; he does not speak when he
                        speaks;</paradox> thus finding his enjoyment outside the dust and dirt (of
                    the world)." The Master considered all this to be a shoreless flow of mere
                    words, and I consider it to describe the course of the Mysterious Way - What do
                    you, Sir, think of it?'</speech></p>
            <p>Chang Wuzi replied, <speech speaker="Chang Wuzi">'The hearing of such words would
                    have perplexed even <ref kind="historical">Huang Di</ref>, and how should <ref
                        kind="historical">Qiu</ref> be competent to understand them? And you,
                    moreover, are too hasty in forming your estimate (of their meaning). You see the
                    egg, and (immediately) look out for the cock (that is to be hatched from it);
                    you see the bow, and (immediately) look out for the dove (that is to be brought
                    down by it) being roasted. I will try to explain the thing to you in a rough
                    way; do you in the same way listen to me. <rhetorical>How could any one stand by
                        the side of the sun and moon, and hold under his arm all space and all
                        time?</rhetorical>
                    <positive>(Such language only means that the sagely man) keeps his mouth shut,
                        and puts aside questions that are uncertain and dark; making his inferior
                        capacities unite with him in honouring (the One Lord).</positive>Men in
                    general bustle about and toil; <negative>the sagely man seems stupid and to know
                        nothing.</negative> He blends ten thousand years together in the one
                    (conception of time); the myriad things all pursue their spontaneous course, and
                    they are all before him as doing so. <rhetorical>How do I know that the love of
                        life is not a delusion? and that the dislike of death is not like a young
                        person's losing his way, and not knowing that he is (really) going home?
                        </rhetorical><ref kind="historical">Li Ji</ref> was a daughter of the border
                    Warden of <ref kind="geographic">Ai</ref>. When (the ruler of) <ref
                        kind="historical">the state of Jin</ref> first got possession of her, she
                    wept till the tears wetted all the front of her dress. But when she came to the
                    place of the king, shared with him his luxurious couch, and ate his
                    grain-and-grass-fed meat, then she regretted that she had wept. How do I know
                    that the dead do not repent of their former craving for life? <comparison
                        topic="dream and reality">Those who dream of (the pleasures of) drinking may
                        in the morning wail and weep; those who dream of wailing and weeping may in
                        the morning be going out to hunt.</comparison><comparison
                        topic="dream and reality">When they were dreaming they did not know it was a
                        dream; in their dream they may even have tried to interpret it; but when
                        they awoke they knew that it was a dream. And there is the great awaking,
                        after which we shall know that this life was a great dream. All the while,
                        the stupid think they are awake, and with nice discrimination insist on
                        their knowledge</comparison>; now playing the part of rulers, and now of
                    grooms. Bigoted was that Qiu! He and you are both dreaming. I who say that you
                    are dreaming am dreaming myself. These words seem very strange; but if after ten
                    thousand ages we once meet with a great sage who knows how to explain them, it
                    will be as if we met him (unexpectedly) some morning or evening.
                        <rhetorical>Since you made me enter into this discussion with you, if you
                        have got the better of me and not I of you, are you indeed right, and I
                        indeed wrong?If I have got the better of you and not you of me, am I indeed
                        right and you indeed wrong? Is the one of us right and the other wrong? are
                        we both right or both wrong? Since we cannot come to a mutual and common
                        understanding, men will certainly continue in darkness on the subject. Whom
                        shall I employ to adjudicate in the matter? If I employ one who agrees with
                        you, how can he, agreeing with you, do so correctly? If I employ one who
                        agrees with me, how can he, agreeing with me, do so correctly? If I employ
                        one who disagrees with you and I, how can he, disagreeing with you and I, do
                        so correctly? If I employ one who agrees with you and I, how can he,
                        agreeing with you and I, do so correctly? In this way I and you and those
                        others would all not be able to come to a mutual understanding; and shall we
                        then wait for that (great sage)? (We need not do so.)</rhetorical> To wait
                    on others to learn how conflicting opinions are changed is simply like not so
                    waiting at all. The harmonising of them is to be found in the invisible
                    operation of Heaven, and by following this on into the unlimited past. It is by
                    this method that we can complete our years (without our minds being disturbed).
                    What is meant by harmonising (conflicting opinions) in the invisible operation
                    of Heaven? <comparison>There is the affirmation and the denial of it; and there
                        is the assertion of an opinion and the rejection of it. If the affirmation
                        be according to the reality of the fact, it is certainly different from the
                        denial of it - there can be no dispute about that. If the assertion of an
                        opinion be correct, it is certainly different from its rejection - neither
                        can there be any dispute about that.</comparison> Let us forget the lapse of
                    time; let us forget the conflict of opinions. Let us make our appeal to the
                    Infinite, and take up our position there.'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="13" type="parable">
            <p>The Penumbra asked the Shadow, saying, <speech speaker="Penumbra">'Formerly you were
                    walking on, and now you have stopped; formerly you were sitting, and now you
                    have risen up - how is it that you are so without stability?'</speech> The
                Shadow replied, <speech speaker="Shadow">'I wait for the movements of something else
                    to do what I do, and that something else on which I wait waits further on
                    another to do as it does. <figurative style="symbolism">My waiting, is it for
                        the scales of a snake, or the wings of a cicada?</figurative> How should I
                    know why I do one thing, or do not do another?</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="14" type="argument">
            <p>Formerly, I, <ref kind="historical">Zhuang Zhou</ref>, dreamt that I was a butterfly,
                a butterfly flying about, feeling that it was enjoying itself. I did not know that
                it was Zhou. Suddenly I awoke, and was myself again, the veritable Zhou. I did not
                know whether it had formerly been Zhou dreaming that he was a butterfly, or it was
                now a butterfly dreaming that it was Zhou. But between Zhou and a butterfly there
                must be a difference. This is a case of what is called the Transformation of
                Things.'</p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter n="3" name="Nourishing the Lord of Life">
        <section n="1" type="argument">
            <!--We are not to pursue what is beyond us. What is right is what is obvious.-->
            <p>There is a limit to our life, but to knowledge there is no limit. With what is
                limited to pursue after what is unlimited is a perilous thing; and when, knowing
                this, we still seek the increase of our knowledge, the peril cannot be averted.
                There should not be the practice of what is good with any thought of the fame (which
                it will bring), nor of what is evil with any approximation to the punishment (which
                it will incur): an accordance with the Central Element (of our nature) is the
                regular way to preserve the body, to maintain the life, to nourish our parents, and
                to complete our term of years. </p>
        </section>
        <section n="2" type="parable">
            <!-- In the cook's repitition of his task, the task itself changed. Thoughts became motions, unaffected by the person executing them. This is what Zhuangzi thinks is right. -->
            <p>His cook was cutting up an ox for the ruler Wen Hui. Whenever he applied his hand,
                leaned forward with his shoulder, planted his foot, and employed the pressure of his
                knee, in the audible ripping off of the skin, and slicing operation of the knife,
                the sounds were all in regular cadence. <figurative style="simile">Movements and
                    sounds proceeded as in the dance of 'the Mulberry Forest' and the blended notes
                    of the King Shou.'</figurative> The ruler said, <speech speaker="King Shou">'Ah!
                    Admirable! That your art should have become so perfect!'</speech> (Having
                finished his operation), the cook laid down his knife, and replied to the remark,
                    <speech speaker="Cook">'What your servant loves is the method of the Dao,
                    something in advance of any art. When I first began to cut up an ox, I saw
                    nothing but the (entire) carcase. After three years I ceased to see it as a
                    whole. Now I deal with it in a spirit-like manner, and <figurative
                        style="metaphor">do not look at it with my eyes.</figurative> The use of my
                    senses is discarded, and my spirit acts as it wills. Observing the natural
                    lines, (my knife) <figurative style="personification">slips through the great
                        crevices and slides through the great cavities, taking advantage of the
                        facilities thus presented.</figurative> My art avoids the membranous
                    ligatures, and much more the great bones. A good cook changes his knife every
                    year; (it may have been injured) in cutting - an ordinary cook changes his every
                    month - (it may have been) broken. Now my knife has been in use for nineteen
                    years; it has cut up several thousand oxen, and yet its edge is as sharp as if
                    it had newly come from the whetstone. There are the interstices of the joints,
                    and the edge of the knife has no (appreciable) thickness; when that which is so
                    thin enters where the interstice is, how easily it moves along! The blade has
                    more than room enough. Nevertheless, whenever I come to a complicated joint, and
                    see that there will be some difficulty, I proceed anxiously and with caution,
                    not allowing my eyes to wander from the place, and moving my hand slowly. Then
                    by a very slight movement of the knife, the part is quickly separated, and
                        <figurative style="simile">drops like (a clod of) earth to the
                        ground</figurative>. Then standing up with the knife in my hand, I look all
                    round, and in a leisurely manner, with an air of satisfaction, wipe it clean,
                    and put it in its sheath.'</speech> The ruler Wen Hui said, <speech
                    speaker="Wen Hui">'Excellent! I have heard the words of my cook, and learned
                    from them the nourishment of (our) life.'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="3" type="parable">
            <!--Natural deformities or other nature-borne errors are "good", in that they do not require reprimanding, because things could not have ever been any other way.-->
            <p>When Gong-wen Xian saw the Master of the Left, he was startled, and said, <speech
                    speaker="Gong-Wen Xian">'What sort of man is this? How is it he has but one
                    foot? Is it from Heaven? or from Man?'</speech> Then he added, <speech
                    speaker="Gong-Wen Xian">'It must be from Heaven, and not from Man. Heaven's
                    making of this man caused him to have but one foot. In the person of man, each
                    foot has its marrow. By this I know that his peculiarity is from Heaven, and not
                    from Man.</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="4" type="parable">
            <p>A pheasant of the marshes has to take ten steps to pick up a mouthful of food, and
                thirty steps to get a drink, but it does not seek to be nourished in a coop. Though
                its spirit would (there) enjoy a royal abundance, it does not think (such
                confinement) good.' </p>
        </section>
        <section n="5" type="parable">
            <!-- Zhuangzi thinks that the best way to honor the dead is to respect the relationship with the deceased. Indulgence in feelings that do not belong to you is to stray from the Dao.-->
            <p>When Lao Dan died, Qin Shi went to console (with his son), but after crying out three
                times, he came out. The disciples said to him, <speech speaker="Disciples">'Were you
                    not a friend of the Master?'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Qin Shi">'I was,'</speech> he replied, and they said, <speech
                    speaker="Disciples">'Is it proper then to offer your condolences merely as you
                    have done?'</speech> He said,<speech speaker="Qin Shi"> 'It is. At first I
                    thought he was the man of men, and now I do not think so. When I entered a
                    little ago and expressed my condolences, there were the <comparison
                        topic="mourning">old men wailing as if they had lost a son</comparison>, and
                    the <comparison topic="mourning">young men wailing as if they had lost their
                        mother</comparison>. In his attracting and uniting them to himself in such a
                    way there must have been that which made them involuntarily express their words
                    (of condolence), and involuntarily wail, as they were doing. And this was a
                    hiding from himself of his Heaven (-nature), and an excessive indulgence of his
                    (human) feelings; a forgetting of what he had received (in being born); what the
                    ancients called the punishment due to neglecting the Heaven (-nature). When the
                    Master came, it was at the proper time; when he went away, it was the simple
                    sequence (of his coming). Quiet acquiescence in what happens at its proper time,
                    and quietly submitting (to its ceasing) afford no occasion for grief or for joy.
                        <ref kind="indirect-quote">The ancients described (death) as the loosening
                        of the cord on which God suspended (the life).</ref></speech>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section n="6" type="argument">
            <!-- Everything is transitional. nothing ever truly appears or disappears, only shifts in form-->
            <p>What we can point to are the faggots that have been consumed; but the fire is
                transmitted (elsewhere), and we know not that it is over and ended.</p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter n="4" name="Man in the World, Associated with other Men">
        <section n="1" type="parable">
            <p>Yan Hui went to see Zhongni, and asked leave to take his departure.<speech
                    speaker="Zhongni">'Where are you going to?'</speech> asked the Master. <speech
                    speaker="Yanhui">'I will go to <ref kind="historical">Wei</ref>'</speech> was
                the reply. <speech speaker="Zhongni">'And with what object?'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Yanhui">'I have heard that <ref kind="geographic">the ruler of
                        Wei</ref> is in the vigour of his years, and consults none but himself as to
                    his course. <figurative style="hyperbole"><negative>He deals with his state as
                            if it were a light matter, and has no perception of his errors. He
                            thinks lightly of his people's dying; the dead are lying all over the
                            country as if no smaller space could contain them; on the plains and
                            about the marshes, they are as thick as heaps of
                        fuel.</negative></figurative> The people know not where to turn to. I have
                    heard you, Master, say, <ref kind="direct-quote">"Leave the state that is well
                        governed; go to the state where disorder prevails."</ref> At the door of a
                    physician there are many who are ill. I wish through what I have heard (from
                    you) to think out some methods (of dealing with <ref kind="geographic"
                    >Wei</ref>), if peradventure the evils of the state may be cured.'</speech></p>
            <p>Zhongni said, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'Alas! The risk is that you will go only to
                    suffer in the punishment (of yourself)! The right method (in such a case) will
                    not admit of any admixture. With such admixture, the one method will become many
                    methods. Their multiplication will embarrass you. That embarrassment will make
                    you anxious. However anxious you may be, you will not save (yourself). The
                    perfect men of old first had (what they wanted to do) in themselves, and
                    afterwards they found (the response to it) in others. <rhetorical>If what they
                        wanted in themselves was not fixed, what leisure had they to go and
                        interfere with the proceedings of any tyrannous man? Moreover, do you know
                        how virtue is liable to be dissipated, and how wisdom proceeds to display
                        itself?</rhetorical><positive>Virtue is dissipated in (the pursuit of) the
                        name for it, and wisdom seeks to display itself in the striving with
                        others.</positive><negative>In the pursuit of the name men overthrow one
                        another; wisdom becomes a weapon of contention. Both these things are
                        instruments of evil, and should not be allowed to have free course in one's
                        conduct.</negative> Supposing one's virtue to be great and his sincerity
                    firm, if he do not comprehend the spirit of those (whom he wishes to influence);
                    and <negative>supposing he is free from the disposition to strive for
                        reputation, if he do not comprehend their minds;-- when in such a case he
                        forcibly insists on benevolence and righteousness, setting them forth in the
                        strongest and most direct language, before the tyrant, then he, hating (his
                        reprover's) possession of those excellences, will put him down as doing him
                        injury.</negative>
                    <paradox>He who injures others is sure to be injured by them in return. You
                        indeed will hardly escape being injured by the man (to whom you
                        go)!</paradox>
                    <rhetorical>Further, if perchance he takes pleasure in men of worth and hates
                        those of an opposite character, what is the use of your seeking to make
                        yourself out to be different (from such men about him)?</rhetorical> Before
                    you have begun to announce (your views), he, as king and ruler, will take
                    advantage of you, and immediately contend with you for victory. Your eyes will
                    be dazed and full of perplexity; you will try to look pleased with him; you will
                    frame your words with care; your demeanour will be conformed to his; you will
                    confirm him in his views.<figurative style="simile">In this way you will be
                        adding fire to fire, and water to water, increasing, as we may express it,
                        the evils (which you deplore).</figurative> To these signs of deferring to
                    him at the first there will be no end. You will be in danger, seeing he does not
                    believe you, of making your words more strong, and you are sure to die at the
                    hands of such a tyrant. And formerly <ref kind="historical">Jie killed Guan
                        Long-feng</ref>, and <ref kind="historical">Zhou killed the prince
                        Bi-gan.</ref>
                    <negative>Both of these cultivated their persons, bending down in sympathy with
                        the lower people to comfort them suffering (as they did) from their
                        oppressors, and on their account opposing their superiors.</negative> On
                    this account, because they so ordered their conduct, their rulers compassed
                    their destruction - such regard had they for their own fame. (Again),<ref
                        kind="historical">Yao anciently attacked (the states of) Cong-qi and
                        Xu-ao</ref>, and <ref kind="historical">Yu attacked the ruler of Hu.</ref>
                    <negative>Those states were left empty, and with no one to continue their
                        population, the people being exterminated. They had engaged in war without
                        ceasing; their craving for whatever they could get was insatiable. And this
                        (ruler of Wei) is, like them, one who craves after fame and greater
                        substance - have you not heard it? Those sages were not able to overcome the
                        thirst for fame and substance - how much less will you be able to do
                        so!</negative> Nevertheless you must have some ground (for the course which
                    you wish to take); pray try and tell it to me.'</speech></p>
            <p>Yan Hui said, <speech speaker="Yanhui">'May I go, doing so in uprightness and
                    humility, using also every endeavour to be uniform (in my plans of
                    operation)?'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Zhongni">'No, indeed!' was the reply. '<negative>How can you do so?
                        This man makes a display of being filled to overflowing (with virtue), and
                        has great self-conceit. His feelings are not to be determined from his
                        countenance. Ordinary men do not (venture to) oppose him, and he proceeds
                        from the way in which he affects them to seek still more the satisfaction of
                        his own mind. He may be described as unaffected by the (small lessons of)
                        virtue brought to bear on him from day to day; and how much less will he be
                        so by your great lessons? He will be obstinate, and refuse to be converted.
                        He may outwardly agree with you, but inwardly there will be no
                        self-condemnation - how can you (go to him in this way and be
                        successful)?'</negative></speech> (Yan Hui) rejoined, <speech
                    speaker="Yanhui">'Well then; <positive>while inwardly maintaining my
                        straightforward intention, I will outwardly seem to bend to him. I will
                        deliver (my lessons), and substantiate them by appealing to antiquity.
                        Inwardly maintaining my straightforward intention, I shall be a co-worker
                        with Heaven.</positive>
                    <comparison topic="heaven">When I thus speak of being a co-worker with Heaven,
                        it is because I know that (the sovereign, whom we style) the son of Heaven,
                        and myself, are equally regarded by Heaven as Its sons. And should I then,
                        as if my words were only my own, be seeking to find whether men approved of
                        them, or disapproved of them? In this way men will pronounce me a (sincere
                        and simple) boy. This is what is called being a co-worker with Heaven.
                        Outwardly bending (to the ruler), I shall be a co-worker with other
                        men.</comparison> To carry (the memorandum tablet to court), to kneel, and
                    to bend the body reverentially - these are the observances of ministers. They
                    all employ them, and should I presume not to do so? Doing what other men do,
                    they would have no occasion to blame me. This is what is called being a
                    fellow-worker with other men. Fully declaring my sentiments and substantiating
                    them by appealing to antiquity, I shall be a co-worker with the ancients.
                    Although the words in which I convey my lessons may really be condemnatory (of
                    the ruler), they will be those of antiquity, and not my own. In this way, though
                    straightforward, I shall be free from blame. This is what is called being a
                    co-worker with antiquity. May I go to <ref kind="geographic">Wei</ref> in this
                    way, and be successful?</speech>' <speech speaker="Zhongni">'No indeed!' said
                    Zhongni. 'How can you do so? You have too many plans of proceeding, and have not
                    spied out (the ruler's character). Though you firmly adhere to your plans, you
                    may be held free from transgression, but this will be all the result. How can
                    you (in this way) produce the transformation (which you desire)? All this only
                    shows (in you) the mind of a teacher!'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="2" type="parable">
            <p>Yan Hui said, <speech speaker="Yanhui">'I can go no farther; I venture to ask the
                    method from you.'</speech> Zhongni replied, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'It is
                    fasting, (as) I will tell you. (But) when you have the method, will you find it
                    easy to practise it? He who thinks it easy will be disapproved of by the bright
                    Heaven.'</speech> Hui said, <speech speaker="Yanhui">'My family is poor. For
                    months together we have no spirituous drink, nor do we taste the proscribed food
                    or any strong-smelling vegetables;-- can this be regarded as fasting?'</speech>
                The reply was, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'It is the fasting appropriate to
                    sacrificing, but it is not the fasting of the mind.'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Yanhui">'I venture to ask what that fasting of the mind
                    is,'</speech> said Hui, and Zhongni answered, <speech speaker="Zhongni"
                        >'<paradox topic="mind and body">Maintain a perfect unity in every movement
                        of your will, You will not wait for the hearing of your ears about it, but
                        for the hearing of your mind. You will not wait even for the hearing of your
                        mind, but for the hearing of the spirit. Let the hearing (of the ears) rest
                        with the ears. Let the mind rest in the verification (of the rightness of
                        what is in the will). But the spirit is free from all pre-occupation and so
                        waits for (the appearance of) things. Where the (proper) course is, there is
                        freedom from all pre-occupation; such freedom is the fasting of the
                        mind.'</paradox></speech> Hui said, <speech speaker="Ynahui">'Before it was
                    possible for me to employ (this method), there I was, the Hui that I am; now,
                    that I can employ it, the Hui that I was has passed away. Can I be said to have
                    obtained this freedom from pre-occupation?'</speech></p>
            <p>The Master replied, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'Entirely. I tell you that you can
                    enter and be at ease in the enclosure (where he is), and not come into collision
                    with the reputation (which belongs to him). If he listen to your counsels, let
                    him hear your notes; if he will not listen, be silent. <figurative
                        style="metaphor">Open no (other) door; employ no other medicine; dwell with
                        him (as with a friend) in the same apartment, and as if you had no other
                        option, and you will not be far from success in your object.</figurative>
                    <comparison topic="mind and body">not to move a step is easy; to walk without
                        treading on the ground is difficult. In acting after the manner of men, it
                        is easy to fall into hypocrisy; in acting after the manner of Heaven, it is
                        difficult to play the hypocrite. I have heard of flying with wings; I have
                        not heard of flying without them. I have heard of the knowledge of the wise;
                        I have not heard of the knowledge of the unwise.</comparison> Look at that
                    aperture (left in the wall); the empty apartment is filled with light through
                    it. Felicitous influences rest (in the mind thus emblemed), as in their proper
                    resting place. Even when they do not so rest, we have what is called (the body)
                    seated and (the mind) galloping abroad. The information that comes through the
                    ears and eyes is comprehended internally, and the knowledge of the mind becomes
                    something external: (when this is the case), the spiritual intelligences will
                    come, and take up their dwelling with us, and how much more will other men do
                    so! All things thus undergo a transforming influence. This was the hinge on
                    which Yu and Shun moved; it was this which Fu-xi and Ji-qu practised all their
                    lives: how much more should other men follow the same rule!'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="3" type="parable">
            <p>Zi Gao, duke of <ref kind="historical">She</ref>, being about to proceed on a mission
                to Qi, asked Zhongni, saying, <speech speaker="Zigao">'The king is sending me, <ref
                        kind="historical">Zhu Liang</ref>, on a mission which is very important. Qi
                    will probably treat me as his commissioner with great respect, but it will not
                    be in a hurry (to attend to the business). Even an ordinary man cannot be
                    readily moved (to action), and how much less the prince of a state! I am very
                    full of apprehension. You, <comparison topic="right and wrong">Sir, once said to
                        me that of all things, great or small, there were few which, if not
                        conducted in the proper way, could be brought to a happy conclusion; that,
                        if the thing were not successful, there was sure to be the evil of being
                        dealt with after the manner of men; that, if it were successful, there was
                        sure to be the evil of constant anxiety; and that, whether it succeeded or
                        not, it was only the virtuous man who could secure its not being followed by
                        evil.</comparison> In my diet I take what is coarse, and do not seek
                    delicacies - a man whose cookery does not require him to be using cooling
                    drinks. This morning I received my charge, and in the evening I am drinking iced
                    water; am I not feeling the internal heat (and discomfort)? Such is my state
                    before I have actually engaged in the affair; I am already suffering from
                    conflicting anxieties. And if the thing do not succeed, (the king) is sure to
                    deal with me after the manner of men. The evil is twofold; as a minister, I am
                    not able to bear the burden (of the mission). Can you, Sir, tell me something
                    (to help me in the case)?'</speech></p>
            <p>Zhongni replied, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'In all things under heaven there are two
                    great cautionary considerations: the one is the requirement implanted (in the
                    nature); the other is the conviction of what is right. The love of a son for his
                    parents is the implanted requirement, and can never be separated from his heart;
                    the service of his ruler by a minister is what is right, and from its obligation
                    there is no escaping anywhere between heaven and earth. These are what are
                    called the great cautionary considerations. Therefore a son finds his rest in
                    serving his parents without reference to or choice of place; and this is the
                    height of filial duty. In the same way a subject finds his rest in serving his
                    ruler, without reference to or choice of the business; and this is the fullest
                    discharge of loyalty. When men are simply obeying (the dictates of) their
                    hearts, the considerations of grief and joy are not readily set before them.
                    They know that there is no alternative to their acting as they do, and rest in
                    it as what is appointed; and this is the highest achievement of virtue. He who
                    is in the position of a minister or of a son has indeed to do what he cannot but
                    do. Occupied with the details of the business (in hand), and forgetful of his
                    own person, what leisure has he to think of his pleasure in living or his
                    dislike of death? You, my master, may well proceed on your mission. But let me
                    repeat to you what I have heard: In all intercourse (between states), if they
                    are near to each other, there should be mutual friendliness, verified by deeds;
                    if they are far apart, there must be sincere adherence to truth in their
                    messages. Those messages will be transmitted by internuncios. But to convey
                    messages which express the complacence or the dissatisfaction of the two parties
                    is the most difficult thing in the world. If they be those of mutual
                    complacence, there is sure to be an overflow of expressions of satisfaction; if
                    of mutual dissatisfaction, an overflow of expressions of dislike. But all
                    extravagance leads to reckless language, and such language fails to command
                    belief. When this distrust arises, woe to the internuncio! Hence the Rules for
                    Speech say, <ref kind="direct-quote">"Transmit the message exactly as it stands;
                        do not transmit it with any overflow of language; so is (the internuncio)
                        likely to keep himself whole."</ref>
                    <comparison>Moreover, skilful wrestlers begin with open trials of strength, but
                        always end with masked attempts (to gain the victory);</comparison> as their
                    excitement grows excessive, they display much wonderful dexterity. Parties
                    drinking according to the rules at first observe good order, but always end with
                    disorder; as their excitement grows excessive, their fun becomes uproarious. In
                    all things it is so. People are at first sincere, but always end with becoming
                    rude; at the commencement things are treated as trivial, but as the end draws
                    near, they assume great proportions. Words are (like) the waves acted on by the
                    wind; <figurative style="simile">the real point of the matters (discussed by
                        them) is lost. The wind and waves are easily set in motion; the success of
                        the matter of which the real point is lost is easily put in peril. Hence
                        quarrels are occasioned by nothing so much as by artful words and one-sided
                        speeches.</figurative> The breath comes angrily, as when a beast, driven to
                    death, wildly bellows forth its rage. On this animosities arise on both sides.
                    Hasty examination (of the case) eagerly proceeds, and revengeful thoughts arise
                    in their minds; they do not know how. Since they do not know how such thoughts
                    arise, who knows how they will end? Hence the Rules for Speech say, <ref
                        kind="indirect-quote">"Let not an internuncius depart from his instructions.
                        Let him not urge on a settlement. If he go beyond the regular rules, he will
                        complicate matters. Departing from his instructions and urging on a
                        settlement imperils negotiations. A good settlement is proved by its lasting
                        long, and a bad settlement cannot be altered - ought he not to be
                        careful?"</ref> Further still, let your mind find its enjoyment in the
                    circumstances of your position; nourish the central course which you pursue, by
                    a reference to your unavoidable obligations. This is the highest object for you
                    to pursue; what else can you do to fulfil the charge (of your father and ruler).
                    The best thing you can do is to be prepared to sacrifice your life; and this is
                    the most difficult thing to do.'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="4" type="parable">
            <p>Yan He, being about to undertake the office of Teacher of the eldest son of <ref
                    kind="historical">duke Ling of Wei</ref>, consulted Qu Bo-yi. <speech
                    speaker="Yanhe">'Here,' said he, 'is this (young) man, whose natural disposition
                    is as bad as it could be. <comparison>If I allow him to proceed in a bad way, it
                        will be at the peril of our state; if I insist on his proceeding in a right
                        way, it will be at the peril of my own person.</comparison> His wisdom is
                    just sufficient to know the errors of other men, but he does not know how he
                    errs himself. What am I to do in such a case?'</speech> Qu Bo-yi replied,<speech
                    speaker="Quboyi">'Good indeed is your question! Be on your guard; be careful;
                    see that you keep yourself correct! Your best plan will be, with your person to
                    seek association with him, and with your mind to try to be in harmony with him;
                    and yet there are dangers connected with both of these things. While seeking to
                    keep near to him, do not enter into his pursuits; while cultivating a harmony of
                    mind with him, do not show how superior you are to him. If in your personal
                    association you enter into his pursuits, you will fall with him and be ruined,
                    you will tumble down with a crash. If in maintaining a harmony with his mind,
                    you show how different you are from him, he will think you do so for the
                    reputation and the name, and regard you as a creature of evil omen.
                        <comparison>If you find him to be a mere boy, be you with him as another
                        boy; if you find him one of those who will not have their ground marked out
                        in the ordinary way, do you humour him in this characteristic; if you find
                        him to be free from lofty airs, show yourself to be the same - (ever)
                        leading him on so as to keep him free from faults.</comparison> Do you not
                    know (the fate of) the praying mantis? It angrily stretches out its arms, to
                    arrest the progress of the carriage, unconscious of its inability for such a
                    task, but showing how much it thinks of its own powers. Be on your guard; be
                    careful. If you cherish a boastful confidence in your own excellence, and place
                    yourself in collision with him, you are likely to incur the fate (of the
                    mantis). <figurative style="simile">Do you not know how those who keep tigers
                        proceed? They do not dare to supply them with living creatures, because of
                        the rage which their killing of them will excite. They do not (even) dare to
                        give them their food whole, because of the rage which their rending of it
                        will excite. They watch till their hunger is appeased, (dealing with them)
                        from their knowledge of their natural ferocity.</figurative>Tigers are
                    different from men, but they fawn on those who feed them, and do so in
                    accordance with their nature. <figurative style="simile">When any of these are
                        killed by them, it is because they have gone against that nature. Those
                        again who are fond of horses preserve their dung in baskets, and their urine
                        in jars. If musquitoes and gadflies light on them, and the grooms brush them
                        suddenly away, the horses break their bits, injure (the ornaments on) their
                        heads, and smash those on their breasts. The more care that is taken of
                        them, the more does their fondness (for their attendants) disappear. Ought
                        not caution to be exercised (in the management of
                    them)?'</figurative></speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="5" type="parable">
            <p>A (master) mechanic, called Shi, on his way to <ref kind="geographic">Qi</ref>, came
                to <ref kind="geographic">Qu-yuan</ref>, where he saw an oak-tree, which was used as
                the altar for the spirits of the land. It was so large that an ox standing behind it
                could not be seen. It measured a hundred spans round, and rose up eighty cubits on
                the hill before it threw out any branches, after which there were ten or so, from
                each of which a boat could be hollowed out. People came to see it in crowds as in a
                market place, but the mechanic did not look round at it, but held on his way without
                stopping. One of his workmen, however, looked long and admiringly at it, and then
                ran on to his master, and said to him, <speech speaker="workman">'Since I followed
                    you with my axe and bill, I have never seen such a beautiful mass of timber as
                    this. Why would you, Sir, not look round at it, but went on without
                    stopping?'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Mr.shi">'Have done,' said Mr. Shi, 'and do not speak about it. It
                    is quite useless. <negative>A boat made from its wood would sink; a coffin or
                        shell would quickly rot; an article of furniture would soon go to pieces; a
                        door would be covered with the exuding sap; a pillar would be riddled by
                        insects; the material of it is good for nothing, and hence it is that it has
                        attained to so great an age.'</negative></speech></p>
            <p>When Mr. Shi was returning, the altar-oak appeared to him in a dream, and said,
                    <speech speaker="altar-oak">'What other tree will you compare with me? Will you
                    compare me to one of your ornamental trees? <negative>There are hawthorns,
                        pear-trees, orange-trees, pummelo-trees, gourds and other low fruit-bearing
                        plants. When their fruits are ripe, they are knocked down from them, and
                        thrown among the dirt. The large branches are broken, and the smaller are
                        torn away.</negative>
                    <comparison>So it is that their productive ability makes their lives bitter to
                        them; they do not complete their natural term of existence, but come to a
                        premature end in the middle of their time, bringing on themselves the
                        destructive treatment which they ordinarily receive. It is so with all
                        things. I have sought to discover how it was that I was so useless; I had
                        long done so, till (the effort) nearly caused my death; and now I have
                        learned it - it has been of the greatest use to
                        me.</comparison><rhetorical>Suppose that I had possessed useful properties,
                        should I have become of the great size that I am? And moreover you and I are
                        both things - how should one thing thus pass its judgment on another? how is
                        it that you a useless man know all this about me a useless
                        tree?'</rhetorical></speech> When Mr. Shih awoke, he kept thinking about his
                dream, but the workman said, <speech speaker="workman">'Being so taken with its
                    uselessness, how is it that it yet acts here as the altar for the spirits of the
                    land?'</speech><speech speaker="Mr.shi"> 'Be still,' was the master's reply,
                    'and do not say a word. It simply happened to grow here; and thus those who do
                    not know it do not speak ill of it as an evil thing. If it were not used as the
                    altar, would it be in danger of being cut down? Moreover, the reason of its
                    being preserved is different from that of the preservation of things generally;
                    is not your explaining it from the sentiment which you have expressed wide of
                    the mark?'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="6" type="parable">
            <p>Nan-bo Zi-Qi in rambling about <ref kind="geographic">the Heights of Shang</ref>, saw
                a large and extraordinary tree. The teams of a thousand chariots might be sheltered
                under it, and its shade would cover them all! Zi-Qi said, <speech
                    speaker="Nanboziqi">'What a tree is this! It must contain an extraordinary
                    amount of timber!</speech> When he looked up, <negative>however, at its smaller
                    branches, they were so twisted and crooked that they could not be made into
                    rafters and beams; when he looked down to its root, its stem was divided into so
                    many rounded portions that neither coffin nor shell could be made from them. He
                    licked one of its leaves, and his mouth felt torn and wounded. The smell of it
                    would make a man frantic, as if intoxicated, for more than three whole days
                    together.</negative>
                <speech speaker="Nanboziqi">'This, indeed,' said he, 'is a tree good for nothing,
                    and it is thus that it has attained to such a size. Ah! and spirit-like men
                    acknowledge this worthlessness (and its result).'</speech> In <ref
                    kind="geographic">Song</ref> there is <ref kind="geographic">the district of
                    Jing-shi</ref>, in which catalpae, cypresses, and mulberry trees grow well.
                Those of them which are a span or two or rather more in circumference are cut down
                by persons who want to make posts to which to tie their monkeys; those which are
                three or four spans round are cut down by persons who want beams forr their lofty
                and famous houses; and those of seven or eight spans are cut down by noblemen and
                rich merchants who want single planks for the sides of their coffins. The trees in
                consequence do not complete their natural term of life, and come to a premature end
                in the middle of their growth under the axe and bill;-- this is the evil that
                befalls them from their supplying good timber. In the same way the Jie (book)
                specifies oxen that have white foreheads, pigs that have turned-up snouts, and men
                that are suffering from piles, and forbids their being sacrificed to <ref
                    kind="historical">the Ho</ref>. <comparison>The wizards know them by these
                    peculiarities and consider them to be inauspicious, but spirit-like men consider
                    them on this account to be very fortunate.</comparison></p>
        </section>
        <section n="7" type="argument">
            <p>There was <ref kind="historical">the deformed object Shu.</ref> His chin seemed to
                hide his navel; his shoulders were higher than the crown of his head; the knot of
                his hair pointed to the sky; his five viscera were all compressed into the upper
                part of his body, and his two thigh bones were like ribs. By sharpening needles and
                washing clothes he was able to make a living. By sifting rice and cleaning it, he
                was able to support ten individuals. When the government was calling out soldiers,
                this poor Shu would bare his arms among the others; when it had any great service to
                be undertaken, because of his constant ailments, none of the work was assigned to
                him; when it was giving out grain to the sick, he received three kung, and ten
                bundles of firewood. <comparison>If this poor man, so deformed in body, was still
                    able to support himself, and complete his term of life, how much more may they
                    do so, whose deformity is that of their faculties!</comparison></p>
        </section>
        <section n="8" type="parable">
            <p>When <ref kind="historical">Confucius</ref> went to <ref kind="geographic">Chu</ref>,
                    <ref kind="historical">Jie-yu</ref>, the madman of Chu, as he was wandering
                about, passed by his door, and said, <speech speaker="Jieyu"><figurative
                        style="irony">0 Phoenix, 0 Phoenix, how is your virtue degenerated! The
                        future is not to be waited for; the past is not to be sought again! When
                        good order prevails in the world, the sage tries to accomplish all his
                        service; when disorder prevails, he may preserve his life; at the present
                        time, it is enough if he simply escape being punished. Happiness is lighter
                        than a feather, but no one knows how to support it; calamity is heavier than
                        the earth, and yet no one knows how to avoid it. Give over! give over
                        approaching men with the lessons of your virtue! You are in peril! you are
                        in peril, hurrying on where you have marked out the ground against your
                        advance! I avoid publicity, I avoid publicity, that my path may not be
                        injured. I pursue my course, now going backwards, now crookedly, that my
                        feet may not be hurt.'</figurative></speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="9" type="argument">
            <p>The mountain by its trees weakens itself. The grease which ministers to the fire
                fries itself. The cinnamon tree can be eaten, and therefore it is cut down. The
                varnish tree is useful, and therefore incisions are made in it. <paradox>All men
                    know the advantage of being useful, but no one knows the advantage of being
                    useless.</paradox></p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter n="5" name="The Seal of Virtue Complete">
        <section type="parable" n="1">
            <p>In Lu there was a Wang Tai who had lost both his feet; while his disciples who
                followed and went about with him were as numerous as those of Zhongni. Chang Ji
                asked Zhongni about him, saying, <speech speaker="Chang Ji">'Though Wang Tai is a
                    cripple, the disciples who follow him about divide Lu equally with you, Master.
                    When he stands, he does not teach them; when he sits, he does not discourse to
                    them. But they go to him empty, and come back full. Is there indeed such a thing
                    as instruction without words? and while the body is imperfect, may the mind be
                    complete? What sort of man is he?'</speech> Zhongni replied, <speech
                    speaker="Zhongni">'This master is a sage. I have only been too late in going to
                    him. I will make him my teacher; and how much more should those do so who are
                    not equal to me! Why should only the state of Lu follow him? I will lead on all
                    under heaven with me to do so.'</speech></p>
            <p> Chang Ji rejoined, <speech speaker="Chang Ji">'He is a man who has lost his feet,
                    and yet he is known as the venerable Wang - he must be very different from
                    ordinary men. What is the peculiar way in which he employs his mind?'</speech>
                The reply was, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'Death and life are great considerations,
                    but they could work no change in him. Though heaven and earth were to be
                    overturned and fall, they would occasion him no loss. His judgment is fixed
                    regarding that in which there is no element of falsehood; and, while other
                    things change, he changes not. The transformations of things are to him the
                    developments prescribed for them, and he keeps fast hold of the author of
                    them.'</speech></p>
            <p>Chang Ji said, <speech speaker="Chang Ji">'What do you mean?'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Zhongni">'When we look at things,'</speech> said Zhongni, <speech
                    speaker="Zhongni">'as they differ, we see them to be different, (as for
                    instance) the liver and the gall, or Chu and Yue; when we look at them, as they
                    agree, we see them all to be a unity. So it is with this (Wang Tai). He takes no
                    knowledge of the things for which his ears and eyes are the appropriate organs,
                    but his mind delights itself in the harmony of (all excellent) qualities. He
                    looks at the unity which belongs to things, and does not perceive where they
                    have suffered loss. He looks on the loss of his feet as only the loss of so much
                    earth.'</speech></p>
            <p>Chang Ji said, <speech speaker="Chang Ji">'He is entirely occupied with his (proper)
                    self. By his knowledge he has discovered (the nature of) his mind, and to that
                    he holds as what is unchangeable; but how is it that men make so much of
                    him?'</speech> The reply was, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'Men do not look into
                    running water as a mirror, but into still water - it is only the still water
                    that can arrest them all, and keep them (in the contemplation of their real
                    selves). Of things which are what they are by the influence of the earth, it is
                    only the pine and cypress which are the best instances - in winter as in summer
                    brightly green. Of those which were what they were by the influence of Heaven,
                    the most correct examples were Yao and Shun; fortunate in (thus) maintaining
                    their own life correct, and so as to correct the lives of others. As a
                    verification of the (power of) the original endowment, when it has been
                    preserved, take the result of fearlessness - how the heroic spirit of a single
                    brave soldier has been thrown into an army of nine hosts. If a man only seeking
                    for fame and able in this way to secure it can produce such an effect, how much
                    more (may we look for a greater result) from one whose rule is over heaven and
                    earth, and holds all things in his treasury, who simply has his lodging in the
                    six members of his body, whom his ears and eyes serve but as conveying
                    emblematic images of things, who comprehends all his knowledge in a unity, and
                    whose mind never dies! If such a man were to choose a day on which he would
                    ascend far on high, men would (seek to) follow him there.<rhetorical> But how
                        should he be willing to occupy himself with other
                    men?'</rhetorical></speech>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section n="2" type="parable">
            <p>Shen-tu Jia was (another) man who had lost his feet. Along with Zi-chan of Zheng he
                studied under the master Bo-hun Wu-ren. Zi-chan said to him (one day), <speech
                    speaker="Zi-chan">'If I go out first, do you remain behind; and if you go out
                    first, I will remain behind.'</speech> Next day they were again sitting together
                on the same mat in the hall, when Zi-chan said (again), <speech speaker="Zi-Chan"
                    >'If I go out first, do you remain behind; and if you go out first, I will
                    remain behind. Now I am about to go out; will you stay behind or not? Moreover,
                    when you see one of official rank (like myself), you do not try to get out of
                    his way - do you consider yourself equal to one of official rank?'</speech>
                Shen-tu Jia replied, <speech speaker="Shen-tu Jia">'In our Master's school is there
                    indeed such recognition required of official rank? You are one, Sir, whose
                    pleasure is in your official rank, and would therefore take precedence of other
                    men. I have heard that when a mirror is bright, the dust does not rest on it;
                    when dust rests on it the mirror is not bright. When one dwells long with a man
                    of ability and virtue, he comes to be without error. There now is our teacher
                    whom you have chosen to make you greater than you are; and when you still talk
                    in this way, are you not in error?'</speech> Zi-chan rejoined, <speech
                    speaker="Zi-chan">'A (shattered) object as you are, you would still strive to
                    make yourself out as good as Yao! If I may form an estimate of your virtue,
                    might it not be sufficient to lead you to the examination of yourself?'</speech>
                The other said, <speech speaker="Shen-tu Jia">'Most criminals, in describing their
                    offences, would make it out that they ought not to have lost (their feet) for
                    them; few would describe them so as to make it appear that they should not have
                    preserved their feet. They are only the virtuous who know that such a calamity
                    was unavoidable, and therefore rest in it as what was appointed for them. When
                    men stand before (an archer like) Yi with his bent bow, if they are in the
                    middle of his field, that is the place where they should be hit; and if they be
                    not hit, that also was appointed. There are many with their feet entire who
                    laugh at me because I have lost my feet, which makes me feel vexed and angry.
                    But when I go to our teacher, I throw off that feeling, and return (to a better
                    mood) - he has washed, without my knowing it, the other from me by (his
                    instructions in) what is good. I have attended him now for nineteen years, and
                    have not known that I am without my feet. Now, you, Sir, and I have for the
                    object of our study the (virtue) which is internal, and not an adjunct of the
                    body, and yet you are continually directing your attention to my external body -
                    are you not wrong in this?'</speech> Zi-chan felt uneasy, altered his manner and
                looks, and said, <speech speaker="Shen-tu Jia">'You need not, Sir, say anything more
                    about it.'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="3" type="parable">
            <p>In Lu there was a cripple, called Shu-shan the Toeless, who came on his heels to see
                Zhongni. Zhongni said to him, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'By your want of
                    circumspection in the past, Sir, you have incurred such a calamity; of what use
                    is your coming to me now?'</speech> Toeless said, <speech speaker="Toeless"
                    >'Through my ignorance of my proper business and taking too little care of my
                    body, I came to lose my feet. But now I am come to you, still possessing what is
                    more honourable than my feet, and which therefore I am anxious to preserve
                    entire. There is nothing which Heaven does not cover, and nothing which Earth
                    does not sustain; you, Master, were regarded by me as doing the part of Heaven
                    and Earth - how could I know that you would receive me in such a way?'</speech>
                Confucius rejoined, <speech speaker="Confucius">'I am but a poor creature. But why,
                    my master, do you not come inside, where I will try to tell you what I have
                    learned?'</speech> When Toeless had gone out, Confucius said, <speech
                    speaker="Confucius">'Be stimulated to effort, my disciples. This toeless cripple
                    is still anxious to learn to make up for the evil of his former conduct;-- how
                    much more should those be so whose conduct has been unchallenged!'</speech> Mr.
                Toeless, however, told Lao Dan (of the interview), saying, <speech speaker="Toeless"
                    >'Kong Qiu, I apprehend, has not yet attained to be a Perfect man.
                        <rhetorical>What has he to do with keeping a crowd of disciples around
                        him?</rhetorical> He is seeking to have the reputation of being an
                    extraordinary and marvellous man, and does not know that the Perfect man
                    considers this to be as handcuffs and fetters to him.'</speech> Lao Dan said,
                    <speech speaker="Lao Dan">'Why did you not simply lead him to see the unity of
                    life and death, and that the admissible and inadmissible belong to one category,
                    so freeing him from his fetters? Would this be possible?'</speech> Toeless said,
                    <speech speaker="Toeless">'It is the punishment inflicted on him by Heaven. How
                    can he be freed from it?'</speech>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section n="4" type="parable">
            <p>Duke Ai of Lu asked Zhongni, saying, <speech speaker="Duke Ai">'There was an ugly man
                    in Wei, called Ai-tai Tuo. His father-in-law, who lived with him, thought so
                    much of him that he could not be away from him. His wife, when she saw him (ugly
                    as he was), represented to her parents, saying, "I had more than ten times
                    rather be his concubine than the wife of any other man." He was never heard to
                    take the lead in discussion, but always seemed to be of the same opinion with
                    others. He had not the position of a ruler, so as to be able to save men from
                    death. He had no revenues, so as to be able to satisfy men's craving for food.
                    He was ugly enough, moreover, to scare the whole world. He agreed with men
                    instead of trying to lead them to adopt his views; <figurative style="hyperbole"
                        >his knowledge did not go beyond his immediate neighbourhood</figurative>.
                    And yet his father-in-law and his wife were of one mind about him in his
                    presence (as I have said) - he must have been different from other men. I called
                    him, and saw him. Certainly he was ugly enough to scare the whole world. He had
                    not lived with me, however, for many months, when I was drawn to the man; and
                    before he had been with me a full year, I had confidence in him. The state being
                    without a chief minister, I (was minded) to commit the government to him. He
                    responded to my proposal sorrowfully, and looked undecided as if he would fain
                    have declined it. I was ashamed of myself (as inferior to him), but finally gave
                    the government into his hands. In a little time, however, he left me and went
                    away. I was sorry and felt that I had sustained a loss, and as if there were no
                    other to share the pleasures of the kingdom with me. What sort of man was
                    he?'</speech></p>
            <p> Zhongni said, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'Once when I was sent on a mission to Qi, I
                    saw some pigs sucking at their dead mother. After a little they looked with
                    rapid glances, when they all left her, and ran away. They felt that she did not
                    see them, and that she was no longer like themselves. What they had loved in
                    their mother was not her bodily figure, but what had given animation to her
                    figure. When a man dies in battle, they do not at his interment employ the usual
                    appendages of plumes: as to supplying shoes to one who has lost his feet, there
                    is no reason why he should care for them - in neither case is there the proper
                    reason for their use. The members of the royal harem do not pare their nails nor
                    pierce their ears; when a man is newly married, he remains (for a time) absent
                    from his official duties, and unoccupied with them. That their bodies might be
                    perfect was sufficient to make them thus dealt with; how much greater results
                    should be expected from men whose mental gifts are perfect! This Ai-tai Tuo was
                    believed by men, though he did not speak a word; and was loved by them, though
                    he did no special service for them. He made men appoint him to the government of
                    their states, afraid only that he would not accept the appointment. He must have
                    been a man whose powers were perfect, though his realisation of them was not
                    manifested in his person.</speech></p>
            <p> Duke Ai said, <speech speaker="Duke Ai">'What is meant by saying that his powers
                    were complete?' Zhongni replied, 'Death and life, preservation and ruin, failure
                    and success, poverty and wealth, superiority and inferiority, blame and praise,
                    hunger and thirst, cold and heat; these are the changes of circumstances, the
                    operation of our appointed lot. Day and night they succeed to one another before
                    us, but there is no wisdom able to discover to what they owe their origination.
                    They are not sufficient therefore to disturb the harmony (of the nature), and
                    are not allowed to enter into the treasury of intelligence. To cause this
                    harmony and satisfaction ever to be diffused, while the feeling of pleasure is
                    not lost from the mind; to allow no break to arise in this state day or night,
                    so that it is always spring-time in his relations with external things; in all
                    his experiences to realise in his mind what is appropriate to each season (of
                    the year): these are the characteristics of him whose powers are
                    perfect.'</speech></p>
            <p><speech speaker="Duke Ai"> 'And what do you mean by the realisation of these powers
                    not being manifested in the person?'</speech> (pursued further the duke). The
                reply was, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'There is nothing so level as the surface of a
                    pool of still water. It may serve as an example of what I mean. All within its
                    circuit is preserved (in peace), and there comes to it no agitation from
                    without. The virtuous efficacy is the perfect cultivation of the harmony (of the
                    nature). Though the realisation of this be not manifested in the person, things
                    cannot separate themselves (from its influence).'</speech></p>
            <p> Some days afterwards duke Ai told this conversation to Min-zi, saying, <speech
                    speaker="Duke Ai">'Formerly it seemed to me the work of the sovereign to stand
                    in court with his face to the south, to rule the kingdom, and to pay good heed
                    to the accounts of the people concerned, lest any should come to a (miserable)
                    death - this I considered to be the sum (of his duty). Now that I have heard
                    that description of the Perfect man, I fear that my idea is not the real one,
                    and that, by employing myself too lightly, I may cause the ruin of my state. I
                    and Kong Qiu are not on the footing of ruler and subject, but on that of a
                    virtuous friendship.'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="5" type="parable">
            <p>A person who had no lips, whose legs were bent so that he could only walk on his
                toes, and who was (otherwise) deformed, addressed his counsels to duke Ling of Wei,
                who was so pleased with him, that he looked on a perfectly formed man as having a
                lean and small neck in comparison with him. Another who had<figurative
                    style="simile"> a large goitre like an earthenware jar</figurative> addressed
                his counsels to duke Huan of Qi, who was so pleased with him that he looked on a
                perfectly formed man as having a neck lean and small in comparison with him. So it
                is that when one's virtue is extraordinary, (any deficiency in) his bodily form may
                be forgotten. When men do not forget what is (easily) forgotten, and forget what is
                not (easily) forgotten, we have a case of real oblivion. <paradox>Therefore the
                    sagely man has that in which his mind finds its enjoyment, and (looks on) wisdom
                    as (but) the shoots from an old stump</paradox>; <figurative style="metaphor"
                    >agreements with others are to him but so much glue</figurative>; <figurative
                    style="metaphor">kindnesses are (but the arts of) intercourse;</figurative> and
                great skill is (but as) merchants' wares. The sagely man lays no plans;
                    <rhetorical>of what use would wisdom be to him?</rhetorical> He has no cutting
                and hacking to do; of <rhetorical>what use would glue be to him?</rhetorical> He has
                lost nothing;<rhetorical> of what use would arts of intercourse be to
                    him?</rhetorical> He has no goods to dispose of; <rhetorical>what need has he to
                    play the merchant? </rhetorical>(The want of) these four things are the
                nourishment of (his) Heavenly (nature); that nourishment is its Heavenly food. Since
                he receives this food from Heaven, <rhetorical>what need has he for anything of
                    man's (devising)?</rhetorical> He has the bodily form of man, but not the
                passions and desires of (other) men. He has the form of man, and therefore he is a
                man. Being without the passions and desires of men, their approvings and
                disapprovings are not to be found in him. How insignificant and small is (the body)
                by which he belongs to humanity! How grand and great is he in the unique perfection
                of his Heavenly (nature)!</p>
        </section>
        <section n="6" type="parable">
            <p>Huizi said to Zhuangzi, <speech speaker="Huizi">'Can a man indeed be without desires
                    and passions?'</speech> The reply was, <speech speaker="Zhuangzi">'He can.'
                    </speech><speech speaker="Huizi">'But on what grounds do you call him a man, who
                    is thus without passions and desires?'</speech> Zhuangzi said, <speech
                    speaker="Zhuangzi">'The Dao gives him his personal appearance (and powers);
                    Heaven gives him his bodily form; how should we not call him a man?'</speech>
                Huizi rejoined, <speech speaker="Huizi"> 'Since you call him a man, how can he be
                    without passions and desires?'</speech> The reply was, <speech
                    speaker="Zhuangzi">'You are misunderstanding what I mean by passions and
                    desires. What I mean when I say that he is without these is, that this man does
                    not by his likings and dislikings do any inward harm to his body - he always
                    pursues his course without effort, and does not (try to) increase his (store of)
                    life.'</speech> Huizi rejoined, <speech speaker="Huizi">'If there were not that
                    increasing of (the amount) of life, how would he get his body?'</speech>
                Zhuangzi said, <speech speaker="Zhuangzi">'The Dao gives him his personal appearance
                    (and powers); Heaven gives him his bodily form; and he does not by his likings
                    and dislikings do any internal harm to his body. But now you, Sir, deal with
                    your spirit as if it were something external to you, and subject your vital
                    powers to toil. You sing (your ditties), leaning against a tree; you go to
                    sleep, grasping the stump of a rotten dryandra tree. Heaven selected for you the
                    bodily form (of a man), and you babble about what is strong and what is
                    white.'</speech></p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter n="6" name="The Great and Most Honoured Master">
        <section n="1" type="argument">
            <p><paradox>He who knows the part which the Heavenly (in him) plays, and knows (also)
                    that which the Human (in him ought to) play, has reached the perfection (of
                    knowledge). He who knows the part which the Heavenly plays (knows) that it is
                    naturally born with him; he who knows the part which the Human ought to play
                    (proceeds) with the knowledge which he possesses to nourish it in the direction
                    of what he does not (yet) know: to complete one's natural term of years and not
                    come to an untimely end in the middle of his course is the fulness of knowledge.
                    Although it be so, there is an evil (attending this condition). Such knowledge
                    still awaits the confirmation of it as correct; it does so because it is not yet
                    determined. </paradox><rhetorical>How do we know that what we call the Heavenly
                    (in us) is not the Human?</rhetorical>
                <rhetorical>and that what we call the Human is not the Heavenly?</rhetorical> There
                must be the True man, and then there is the True knowledge. </p>
            <p><rhetorical>What is meant by 'the True Man?'</rhetorical>
                <paradox>The True men of old did not reject (the views of) the few; they did not
                    seek to accomplish (their ends) like heroes (before others); they did not lay
                    plans to attain those ends. Being such, though they might make mistakes, they
                    had no occasion for repentance; though they might succeed, they had no
                    self-complacency. Being such, they could ascend the loftiest heights without
                    fear; they could pass through water without being made wet by it; they could go
                    into fire without being burnt;</paradox> so it was that by their knowledge they
                ascended to and reached the Dao. </p>
            <p><paradox>The True men of old did not dream when they slept, had no anxiety when they
                    awoke, and did not care that their food should be pleasant. Their breathing came
                    deep and silently. The breathing of the true man comes (even) from his heels,
                    while men generally breathe (only) from their throats. When men are defeated in
                    argument, their words come from their gullets as if they were vomiting. Where
                    lusts and desires are deep, the springs of the Heavenly are shallow.</paradox>
            </p>
            <p>The True men of old knew nothing of the love of life or of the hatred of death.
                Entrance into life occasioned them no joy; the exit from it awakened no resistance.
                Composedly they went and came. They did not forget what their beginning bad been,
                and they did not inquire into what their end would be. They accepted (their life)
                and rejoiced in it; they forgot (all fear of death), and returned (to their state
                before life). Thus there was in them what is called the want of any mind to resist
                the Dao, and of all attempts by means of the Human to assist the Heavenly. Such were
                they who are called the True men. Being such, their minds were free from all
                thought; their demeanour was still and unmoved; <figurative style="personification"
                    >their foreheads beamed simplicity.</figurative>
                <figurative style="simile">Whatever coldness came from them was like that of autumn;
                    whatever warmth came from them was like that of spring. Their joy and anger
                    assimilated to what we see in the four seasons.</figurative> They did in regard
                to all things what was suitable, and no one could know how far their action would
                go. Therefore the sagely man might, in his conduct of war, <paradox>destroy a state
                    without losing the hearts of the people;</paradox>
                <paradox>his benefits and favours might extend to a myriad generations without his
                    being a lover of men.</paradox> Hence he who tries to share his joys with others
                is not a sagely man; he who manifests affection is not benevolent; he who observes
                times and seasons (to regulate his conduct) is not a man of wisdom; he to whom
                profit and injury are not the same is not a superior man; he who acts for the sake
                of the name of doing so, and loses his (proper) self is not the (right) scholar; and
                he who throws away his person in a way which is not the true (way) cannot command
                the service of others. <ref kind="historical">Such men as Hu Bu-jie, Wu Guang,
                    Bo-yi, Shu-Qi, the count of Ji, Xu-yu, Ji Ta, and Shen-tu Di</ref>, all did
                service for other men, and sought to secure for them what they desired, not seeking
                their own pleasure. </p>
            <p><paradox><positive>The True men of old presented the aspect of judging others aright,
                        but without being partisans; of feeling their own insufficiency, but being
                        without flattery or cringing. Their peculiarities were natural to them, but
                        they were not obstinately attached to them; their humility was evident, but
                        there was nothing of unreality or display about it. Their placidity and
                        satisfaction had the appearance of joy; their every movement seemed to be a
                        necessity to them. Their accumulated attractiveness drew men's looks to
                        them; their blandness fixed men's attachment to their virtue. They seemed to
                        accommodate themselves to the (manners of their age), but with a certain
                        severity; their haughty indifference was beyond its control. Unceasing
                        seemed their endeavours to keep (their mouths) shut; when they looked down,
                        they had forgotten what they wished to say. They considered punishments to
                        be the substance (of government, and they never incurred it); ceremonies to
                        be its supporting wings (and they always observed them); wisdom (to
                        indicate) the time (for action, and they always selected it); and virtue to
                        be accordance (with others), and they were all-accordant. Considering
                        punishments to be the substance (of government), yet their generosity
                        appeared in the (manner of their) infliction of death. Considering
                        ceremonies to be its supporting wings, they pursued by means of them their
                        course in the world. Considering wisdom to indicate the time (for action),
                        they felt it necessary to employ it in (the direction of) affairs.
                        Considering virtue to be accordance (with others), they sought to ascend its
                        height along with all who had feet (to climb it). (Such were they), and yet
                        men really thought that they did what they did by earnest effort. In this
                        way they were one and the same in all their likings and dislikings. Where
                        they liked, they were the same; where they did not like, they were the same.
                        In the former case where they liked, they were fellow-workers with the
                        Heavenly (in them); in the latter where they disliked, they were co-workers
                        with the Human in them. The one of these elements (in their nature) did not
                        overcome the other. Such were those who are called the True
                    men.</positive></paradox></p>
        </section>
        <section n="2" type="argument">
            <p>Death and life are ordained, just as we have the constant succession of night and day
                - in both cases from Heaven. Men have no power to do anything in reference to them -
                such is the constitution of things. There are those who specially regard Heaven as
                their father, and they still love It (distant as It is); how much more should they
                love That which stands out (Superior and Alone)! Some specially regard their ruler
                as superior to themselves, and will give their bodies to die for him; how much more
                should they do so for That which is their true (Ruler)! <figurative topic="fish"
                    style="metaphor">When the springs are dried up, the fishes collect together on
                    the land. Than that they should moisten one another there by the damp about
                    them, and keep one another wet by their slime, it would be better for them to
                    forget one another in the rivers and lakes.</figurative> And <ref
                    kind="historical">when men praise Yao and condemn Jie</ref>, it would be better
                to forget them both, and seek the renovation of the Dao.</p>
            <p>There is the great Mass (of nature) - I find the support of my body on it; my life is
                spent in toil on it; my old age seeks ease on it; at death I find rest in it - what
                makes my life a good makes my death also a good. If you hide away a boat in the
                ravine of a hill, and hide away the hill in a lake, you will say that (the boat) is
                secure; but at midnight there shall come a strong man and carry it off on his back,
                while you in the dark know nothing about it. You may hide away anything, whether
                small or great, in the most suitable place, and yet it shall disappear from it.
                    <paradox topic="World">But if you could hide the world in the world, so that
                    there was nowhere to which it could be removed, this would be the grand reality
                    of the ever-during Thing.</paradox> When the body of man comes from its special
                mould, there is even then occasion for joy; but this body undergoes a myriad
                transformations, and does not immediately reach its perfection; <rhetorical>does it
                    not thus afford occasion for joys incalculable?</rhetorical> Therefore the
                sagely man enjoys himself in that from which there is no possibility of separation,
                and by which all things are preserved. He considers early death or old age, his
                beginning and his ending, all to be good, and in this other men imitate him; how
                much more will they do so in regard to That Itself on which all things depend, and
                from which every transformation arises!</p>
        </section>
        <section n="3" type="argument">
            <p>This is the Dao; <paradox>there is in It emotion and sincerity, but It does nothing
                    and has no bodily form. It may be handed down (by the teacher), but may not be
                    received (by his scholars). It may be apprehended (by the mind), but It cannot
                    be seen. It has Its root and ground (of existence) in Itself.</paradox> Before
                there were heaven and earth, from of old, there It was, securely existing. From It
                came the mysterious existences of spirits, from It the mysterious existence of God.
                    <paradox>It produced heaven; It produced earth. It was before the Tai-ji, and
                    yet could not be considered high</paradox>;<paradox> It was below all space, and
                    yet could not be considered deep.</paradox>
                <paradox>It was produced before heaven and earth, and yet could not be considered to
                    have existed long;</paradox>
                <paradox>It was older than the highest antiquity, and yet could not be considered
                    old.</paradox><ref kind="historical"> Shi-wei got It, and by It adjusted heaven
                    and earth. Fu-xi got It, and by It penetrated to the mystery of the maternity of
                    the primary matter. The Wei-dou got It, and from all antiquity has made no
                    eccentric movement. The Sun and Moon got It, and from all antiquity have not
                    intermitted (their bright shining). Kan-pei got It, and by It became lord of
                    Kun-lun. Feng-yi got It, and by It enjoyed himself in the Great River. Jian-wu
                    got It, and by It dwelt on mount Tai. Huang-di got It, and by It ascended the
                    cloudy sky. Zhuan-xu got It, and by It dwelt in the Dark Palace. Yu-jiang got
                    It, and by It was set on the North Pole. Xi Wang-mu got It, and by It had her
                    seat in (the palace of) Shao-guang. No one knows Its beginning; no one knows Its
                    end. Peng Zu got It, and lived on from the time of the lord of Yu to that of the
                    Five Chiefs. Fu Yue got It, and by It became chief minister to Wu-ding, (who
                    thus) in a trice became master of the kingdom. (After his death), Fu Yue mounted
                    to the eastern portion of the Milky Way, where, riding on Sagittarius and
                    Scorpio, he took his place among the stars.</ref></p>
        </section>
        <section n="4" type="parable">
            <p>Nan-bo Zi-kui asked Nu Yu, saying, <speech speaker="Nan-bo Zi-kui">'You are old, Sir,
                    while <figurative style="simile">your complexion is like that of a
                        child</figurative>; how is it so?'</speech> The reply was, <speech
                    speaker="Nu Yu">'I have become acquainted with the Dao.'</speech> The other
                said, <speech speaker="Nan-bo Zi-kui">'Can I learn the Dao?'</speech> Nu Yu said,
                    <speech speaker="Nu Yu">'No. <rhetorical>How can you?</rhetorical> You, Sir, are
                    not the man to do so. There was Bu-liang Yi who had the abilities of a sagely
                    man, but not the Dao, while I had the Dao, but not the abilities. I wished,
                    however, to teach him, if, peradventure, he might become the sagely man indeed.
                    If he should not do so, it was easy (I thought) for one possessing the Dao of
                    the sagely man to communicate it to another possessing his abilities.
                    Accordingly, I proceeded to do so, but with deliberation. After three days, he
                    was able to banish from his mind all worldly (matters). This accomplished, I
                    continued my intercourse with him in the same way; and in seven days he was able
                    to banish from his mind all thought of men and things. This accomplished, and my
                    instructions continued, after nine days, he was able to count his life as
                    foreign to himself. This accomplished, his mind was afterwards clear as the
                    morning; and after this he was able to see his own individuality. That
                    individuality perceived, he was able to banish all thought of Past or Present.
                    Freed from this, he was able to penetrate to (the truth that there is no
                    difference between) life and death - (how) the destruction of life is not dying,
                    and the communication of other life is not living. (The Dao) is a thing which
                    accompanies all other things and meets them, which is present when they are
                    overthrown and when they obtain their completion. Its name is Tranquillity amid
                    all Disturbances, meaning that such Disturbances lead to Its
                    Perfection.'</speech></p>
            <p><speech speaker="Nan-bo Zi-kui">'And how did you, being alone (without any teacher),
                    learn all this?'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Nu Yu">'I learned it,'</speech> was the reply, <speech
                    speaker="Nu Yu">'from the son of Fu-mo; he learned it from the grandson of
                    Luo-song; he learned it from Zhan-ming; he learned it from Nie-xu; he, from
                    Xu-yu; he, from Ou; he, from Xuan-ming; he, from Shen-liao; and he learned it
                    from Yi-shi.'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="5" type="parable">
            <p>Zi-si, Zi-yu, Zi-li, and Zi-lai, these four men, were talking together, when some one
                said, <speech speaker="Zi-si, Zi-yu, Zi-li, or Zi-lai"><rhetorical>'Who can suppose
                        the head to be made from nothing, the spine from life, and the rump-bone
                        from death?</rhetorical>
                    <rhetorical>Who knows how death and birth, living on and disappearing, compose
                        the one body?</rhetorical> I would be friends with him.'</speech> The four
                men looked at one another and laughed, but no one seized with his mind the drift of
                the questions. All, however, were friends together. Not long after Zi-yu fell ill,
                and Zi-si went to inquire for him. <speech speaker="Zi-yu">'How great,'</speech>
                said (the sufferer), <speech speaker="Zi-yu">'is the Creator! That He should have
                    made me the deformed object that I am!'</speech> He was a crooked hunchback; his
                five viscera were squeezed into the upper part of his body; his chin bent over his
                navel; his shoulder was higher than his crown; on his crown was an ulcer pointing to
                the sky; his breath came and went in gasps: yet he was easy in his mind, and made no
                trouble of his condition. He limped to a well, looked at himself in it, and said,
                    <speech speaker="Zi-yu">'Alas that the Creator should have made me the deformed
                    object that I am!'</speech> Si said, <speech speaker="Si">'Do you dislike your
                    condition?'</speech> He replied, <speech speaker="Zi-yu">'<rhetorical
                        topic="sickness">No, why should I dislike it?</rhetorical> If He were to
                    transform my left arm into a cock, I should be watching with it the time of the
                    night; if He were to transform my right arm into a cross-bow, I should then be
                    looking for a Xiao to (bring down and) roast; if He were to transform my
                    rump-bone into a wheel, and my spirit into a horse, I should then be mounting
                    it, and would not change it for another steed. Moreover, when we have got (what
                    we are to do), there is the time (of life) in which to do it; when we lose that
                    (at death), submission (is what is required). When we rest in what the time
                    requires, and manifest that submission, neither joy nor sorrow can find entrance
                    (to the mind). This would be what the ancients called loosing the cord by which
                    (the life) is suspended. But one hung up cannot loose himself;-- he is held fast
                    by his bonds. And that creatures cannot overcome Heaven (the inevitable) is a
                    long-acknowledged fact - <rhetorical topic="sickness">why should I hate my
                        condition?</rhetorical>'</speech></p>
            <p>Before long Zi-lai fell ill, and lay gasping at the point of death, while his wife
                and children stood around him wailing. Zi-li went to ask for him, and said to them,
                    <speech speaker="Zi-li">'Hush! Get out of the way! Do not disturb him as he is
                    passing through his change.'</speech> Then, leaning against the door, he said
                (to the dying man), <speech speaker="Zi-li">'Great indeed is the Creator!
                        <rhetorical topic="Death">What will He now make you to become? Where will He
                        take you to? Will He make you the liver of a rat, or the arm of an
                        insect?</rhetorical></speech> Zi-lai replied, <speech speaker="Zi-lai"
                    >'Wherever a parent tells a son to go, east, west, south, or north, he simply
                    follows the command. The Yin and Yang are more to a man than his parents are. If
                    they are hastening my death, and I do not quietly submit to them, I shall be
                    obstinate and rebellious. There is the great Mass (of nature);-- I find the
                    support of my body in it; my life is spent in toil on it; my old age seeks ease
                    on it; at death I find rest on it: what has made my life a good will make my
                    death also a good. Here now is a great founder, casting his metal. If the metal
                    were to leap up (in the pot), and say, "I must be made into a (sword like the)
                    Mo-ye," the great founder would be sure to regard it as uncanny. So, again, when
                    a form is being fashioned in the mould of the womb, if it were to say, "I must
                    become a man; I must become a man," the Creator would be sure to regard it as
                    uncanny. When we once understand that heaven and earth are a great melting-pot,
                    and the Creator a great founder, <rhetorical topic="Purpose">where can we have
                        to go to that shall not be right for us?</rhetorical> We are born as from a
                    quiet sleep, and we die to a calm awaking.'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="6" type="parable">
            <p>Zi-sang Hu, Meng Zi-fan, and Zi-qin Zhang, these three men, were friends together.
                (One of them said), <speech speaker="Zi-sang Hu, Meng Zi-fan, or Zi-qin Zhang"
                        ><rhetorical>'Who can associate together without any (thought of) such
                        association, or act together without any (evidence of) such co-operation?
                        </rhetorical><rhetorical>Who can mount up into the sky and enjoy himself
                        amidst the mists, disporting beyond the utmost limits (of things), and
                        forgetting all others as if this were living, and would have no
                        end?</rhetorical>'</speech> The three men looked at one another and laughed,
                not perceiving the drift of the questions; and they continued to associate together
                as friends. Suddenly, after a time, Zi-sang Hu died. Before he was buried, Confucius
                heard of the event, and sent Zi-gong to go and see if he could render any
                assistance. One of the survivors had composed a ditty, and the other was playing on
                his lute. Then they sang together in unison,</p>
            <p><speech speaker="Meng Zi-fan and Zi-qin Zhang">'Ah! come, Sang Hu! ah! come, Sang Hu!
                    Your being true you've got again, While we, as men, still here remain
                    Ohone!'</speech></p>
            <p>Zi-gong hastened forward to them, and said, <speech speaker="Zi-gong">'I venture to
                    ask whether it be according to the rules to be singing thus in the presence of
                    the corpse?'</speech> The two men looked at each other, and laughed, saying,
                'What does this man know about the idea that underlies (our) rules?' Zi-gong
                returned to Confucius, and reported to him, saying, <speech
                    speaker="Meng Zi-fan and Zi-qin Zhang">'What sort of men are those? They had
                    made none of the usual preparations, and treated the body as a thing foreign to
                    them. They were singing in the presence of the corpse, and there was no change
                    in their countenances. I cannot describe them; what sort of men are
                    they?'</speech> Confucius replied, <speech speaker="Confucius">'Those men occupy
                    and enjoy themselves in what is outside the (common) ways (of the world), while
                    I occupy and enjoy myself in what lies within those ways. There is no common
                    ground for those of such different ways; and when I sent you to condole with
                    those men, I was acting stupidly. They, moreover, make man to be the fellow of
                    the Creator, and seek their enjoyment in the formless condition of heaven and
                    earth. They consider life to be an appendage attached, an excrescence annexed to
                    them, and death to be a separation of the appendage and a dispersion of the
                    contents of the excrescence. With these views, <rhetorical>how should they know
                        wherein death and life are to be found, or what is first and what is
                        last?</rhetorical> They borrow different substances, and pretend that the
                    common form of the body is composed of them. They dismiss the thought of (its
                    inward constituents like) the liver and gall, and (its outward constituents),
                    the ears and eyes. Again and again they end and they begin, having no knowledge
                    of first principles. They occupy themselves ignorantly and vaguely with what
                    (they say) lies outside the dust and dirt (of the world), and seek their
                    enjoyment in the business of doing nothing. <rhetorical>How should they
                        confusedly address themselves to the ceremonies practised by the common
                        people, and exhibit themselves as doing so to the ears and eyes of the
                        multitude?'</rhetorical></speech></p>
            <p>Zi-gong said, <speech speaker="Zi-gong">'Yes, but why do you, Master, act according
                    to the (common) ways (of the world)?'</speech> The reply was, <speech
                    speaker="Confucius">'I am in this under the condemning sentence of Heaven.
                    Nevertheless, I will share with you (what I have attained to).'</speech> Zi-gong
                rejoined, <speech speaker="Zi-gong">'I venture to ask the method which you
                    pursue;'</speech> and Confucius said, <speech speaker="Confucius">'Fishes breed
                    and grow in the water; man developes in the Dao. Growing in the water,
                        <figurative style="personification">the fishes cleave the
                    pools</figurative>, and their nourishment is supplied to them. Developing in the
                    Dao, men do nothing, and the enjoyment of their life is secured. Hence it is
                    said, "Fishes forget one another in the rivers and lakes; men forget one another
                    in the arts of the Dao."'</speech> Zi-gong said, <speech speaker="Zi-gong">'I
                    venture to ask about the man who stands aloof from others.'</speech> The reply
                was, <speech speaker="Confucius">'He stands aloof from other men, but he is in
                    accord with Heaven! Hence it is said, "The small man of Heaven is the superior
                    man among men; the superior man among men is the small man of Heaven!"'</speech>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section n="7" type="parable">
            <p> Yan Hui asked Zhongni, saying, <speech speaker="Yan Hui">'When the mother of
                    Meng-sun Cai died, in all his wailing for her he did not shed a tear; in the
                    core of his heart he felt no distress; during all the mourning rites, he
                    exhibited no sorrow. Without these three things, he (was considered to have)
                    discharged his mourning well; is it that in the state of Lu one who has not the
                    reality may yet get the reputation of having it? I think the matter very
                    strange.'</speech> Zhongni said, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'That Meng-sun
                    carried out (his views) to the utmost. He was advanced in knowledge; but (in
                    this case) <paradox>it was not possible for him to appear to be negligent (in
                        his ceremonial observances)', but he succeeded in being really so to
                        himself</paradox>. Meng-sun does not know either what purposes life serves,
                    or what death serves; he does not know which should be first sought, and which
                    last. If he is to be transformed into something else, he will simply await the
                    transformation which he does not yet know. This is all he does. And moreover,
                    when one is about to undergo his change, <rhetorical>how does he know that it
                        has not taken place?</rhetorical> And <rhetorical>when he is not about to
                        undergo his change, how does he know that it has taken place?</rhetorical>
                    Take the case of me and you: <rhetorical>are we in a dream from which we have
                        not begun to awake?</rhetorical> Moreover, Meng-sun presented in his body
                    the appearance of being agitated, but in his mind he was conscious of no loss.
                        <figurative style="simile">The death was to him like the issuing from one's
                        dwelling at dawn</figurative>, and no (more terrible) reality. He was more
                    awake than others were. When they wailed, he also wailed, having in himself the
                    reason why he did so. And we all have our individuality which makes us what we
                    are as compared together; <rhetorical>but how do we know that we determine in
                        any case correctly that individuality?</rhetorical> Moreover you dream that
                    you are a bird, and seem to be soaring to the sky; or that you are a fish, and
                    seem to be diving in the deep. But you do not know whether we that are now
                    speaking are awake or in a dream. It is not the meeting with what is pleasurable
                    that produces the smile; it is not the smile suddenly produced that produces the
                    arrangement (of the person). When one rests in what has been arranged, and puts
                    away all thought of the transformation, he is in unity with the mysterious
                    Heaven.'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="8" type="parable">
            <p> Yi-er Zi having gone to see Xu You, the latter said to him, <speech speaker="Xu You"
                    >'What benefit have you received from Yao?'</speech> The reply was, <speech
                    speaker="Yi-er Zi">'Yao says to me, You must yourself labour at benevolence and
                    righteousness, and be able to tell clearly which is right and which wrong (in
                    conflicting statements).'</speech> Xu You rejoined, <speech speaker="Xu You"
                    >'Why then have you come to me? Since Yao has put on you the brand of his
                    benevolence and righteousness, and cut off your nose with his right and wrong,
                    how will you be able to wander in the way of aimless enjoyment, of unregulated
                    contemplation, and the ever-changing forms (of dispute)?'</speech> Yi-er Zi
                said, <speech speaker="Yi-er Zi">'That may be; but I should like to skirt along its
                    hedges.'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Xu You">'But,'</speech> said the other, <speech speaker="Xu You"
                    >'it cannot be. Eyes without pupils can see nothing of the beauty of the
                    eyebrows, eyes, and other features; the blind have nothing to do with the green,
                    yellow, and variegated colours of the sacrificial robes.'</speech> Yi-er Zi
                rejoined, <speech speaker="Yi-er Zi">'Yet, when Wu-zhuang lost his beauty, Ju-liang
                    his strength, and Huang-Di his wisdom, they all (recovered them) under the
                    moulding (of your system) - how do you know that the Maker will not obliterate
                    the marks of my branding, and supply my dismemberment, so that, again perfect in
                    my form, I may follow you as my teacher?'</speech> Xu You said, <speech
                    speaker="Xu You">'Ah! that cannot yet be known. I will tell you the rudiments. 0
                    my Master! 0 my Master! He gives to all things their blended qualities, and does
                    not count it any righteousness; His favours reach to all generations, and He
                    does not count it any benevolence; He is more ancient than the highest
                    antiquity, and does not count Himself old; He overspreads heaven and supports
                    the earth; He carves and fashions all bodily forms, and does not consider it any
                    act of skill;-- this is He in whom I find my enjoyment.'</speech>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section n="9" type="parable">
            <p>Yan Hui said, <speech speaker="Yan Hui">'I am making progress.'</speech> Zhongni
                replied, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'What do you mean?'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Yan Hui">'I have ceased to think of benevolence and
                    righteousness,'</speech> was the reply. <speech speaker="Zhongni">'Very well;
                    but that is not enough.'</speech> Another day, Hui again saw Zhongni, and said,
                    <speech speaker="Yan Hui">'I am making progress.'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Zhongni">'What do you mean?'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Yan Hui">'I have lost all thought of ceremonies and
                    music.'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Zhongni">'Very well, but that is not enough.'</speech> A third day,
                Hui again saw (the Master), and said, <speech speaker="Yan Hui">'I am making
                    progress.'</speech>
                <speech speaker="Zhongni">'What do you mean?'</speech><speech speaker="Yan Hui"> 'I
                    sit and forget everything.'</speech> Zhongni changed countenance, and said,
                    <speech speaker="Zhongni">'What do you mean by saying that you sit and forget
                    (everything)?'</speech> Yan Hui replied, <speech speaker="Yan Hui">'My connexion
                    with the body and its parts is dissolved; my perceptive organs are discarded.
                    Thus leaving my material form, and bidding farewell to my knowledge, I am become
                    one with the Great Pervader. This I call sitting and forgetting all
                    things.'</speech> Zhongni said, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'One (with that
                    Pervader), you are free from all likings; so transformed, you are become
                    impermanent. You have, indeed, become superior to me! I must ask leave to follow
                    in your steps.'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="10" type="parable">
            <p>Zi-yu and Zi-sang were friends. (Once), when it had rained continuously for ten days,
                Zi-yu said, <speech speaker="Zi-yu">'I fear that Zi-sang may be in
                    distress.'</speech> So he wrapped up some rice, and went to give it to him to
                eat. When he came to Zi-sang's door, there issued from it sounds between singing and
                wailing; a lute was struck, and there came the words,<speech speaker="Zi-sang"> '0
                    Father! 0 Mother! 0 Heaven! 0 Men!'</speech> The voice could not sustain itself,
                and the line was hurriedly pronounced. Zi-yu entered and said, <speech
                    speaker="Zi-yu">'Why are you singing, Sir, this line of poetry in such a
                    way?'</speech> The other replied, <speech speaker="Zi-sang">'I was thinking, and
                    thinking in vain, how it was that I was brought to such extremity.<rhetorical
                        topic="Fairness"> Would my parents have wished me to be so
                        poor?</rhetorical> Heaven overspreads all without any partial feeling, and
                    so does Earth sustain all; <rhetorical><figurative style="personification">Would
                            Heaven and Earth make me so poor with any unkindly
                        feeling?</figurative></rhetorical> I was trying to find out who had done it,
                    and I could not do so. But here I am in this extremity - it is what was
                    appointed for me!'</speech></p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter n="7" name="The Normal Course for Rulers and Kings">
        <section n="1" type="parable">
            <p>Nie Que put four questions to Wang Ni, not one of which did he know (how to answer).
                On this Nie Que leaped up, and in great delight walked away and informed Yu-yi Zi of
                it, who said to him, <speech speaker="Yuyizi">'Do you (only) now know it?' He of the
                    line of <ref kind="historical">Yu</ref> was not equal to him of the line of <ref
                        kind="historical">Tai</ref>. He of Yu still kept in himself (the idea of)
                    benevolence by which to constrain (the submission of) men; and he did win men,
                    but he had not begun to proceed by what did not belong to him as a man. He of
                    the line of Tai would sleep tranquilly, and awake in contented simplicity. He
                    would consider himself now (merely) as a horse, and now (merely) as an ox. His
                    knowledge was real and untroubled by doubts; and his virtue was very true: he
                    had not begun to proceed by what belonged to him as a man.'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="2" type="parable">
            <p>Jian Wu went to see the mad (recluse), Jie-yu, who said to him, <speech
                    speaker="Jieyu">'What did <ref kind="historical">Ri-Zhong Shi</ref> tell
                    you?'</speech> The reply was, <speech speaker="Jianwu">'He told me that when
                    rulers gave forth their regulations according to their own views and enacted
                    righteous measures, no one would venture not to obey them, and all would be
                    transformed.'</speech> Jie-yu said, <speech speaker="Jieyu">'That is but the
                    hypocrisy of virtue. For the right ordering of the world it would be like trying
                    to wade through the sea and dig through the He, or employing a mosquito to carry
                    a mountain on its back. And when a sage is governing, does he govern men's
                    outward actions? He is (himself) correct, and so (his government) goes on; this
                    is the simple and certain way by which he secures the success of his affairs.
                        <figurative style="metaphor">Think of the bird which flies high, to avoid
                        being hurt by the dart on the string of the archer, and the little mouse
                        which makes its hole deep under Shen-qiu to avoid the danger of being smoked
                        or dug out; are (rulers) less knowing than these two little
                        creatures?'</figurative></speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="3" type="parable">
            <p>Tian Gen, rambling on the south of <ref kind="geographic">(mount) Yin</ref>, came to
                the neighbourhood of the <ref kind="geographic">Liao-water</ref>. Happening there to
                meet with the man whose name is not known, he put a question to him, saying, <speech
                    speaker="Tiangen">'I beg to ask what should be done in order to (carry on) the
                    government of the world.'</speech> The nameless man said, <speech
                    speaker="The nameless man">'Go away; you are a rude borderer. Why do you put to
                    me a question for which you are unprepared? I would simply play the part of the
                    Maker of (all) things. When wearied, I would mount on the bird of the light and
                    empty air, proceed beyond the six cardinal points, and wander in the region of
                    nonentity, to dwell in the wilderness of desert space. What method have you,
                    moreover, for the government of the world that you (thus) agitate my
                    mind?'</speech> (Tian Gen), however, again asked the question, and the nameless
                man said, <speech speaker="Tiangen">'Let your mind find its enjoyment in pure
                    simplicity; blend yourself with (the primary) ether in idle indifference; allow
                    all things to take their natural course; and admit no personal or selfish
                    consideration - do this and the world will be governed.'</speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="4" type="parable">
            <p>Yang Zi-ju, having an interview with Lao Dan, said to him, <speech speaker="Yangziju"
                        >'<positive>Here is a man, alert and vigorous in responding to all matters,
                        clearsighted and widely intelligent, and an unwearied student of the Dao -
                        can he be compared to one of the intelligent kings?'</positive></speech> The
                reply was, <speech speaker="Laodan">'<negative>Such a man is to one of the
                        intelligent kings but as the bustling underling of a court who toils his
                        body and distresses his mind with his various contrivances. And moreover, it
                        is the beauty of the skins of the tiger and leopard which makes men hunt
                        them; the agility of the monkey, or (the sagacity of) the dog that catches
                        the yak, which make men lead them in strings; but can one similarly endowed
                        be compared to the intelligent kings?'</negative></speech> Yang Zi-ju looked
                discomposed and said, <speech speaker="Yangziju">'I venture to ask you what the
                    government of the intelligent kings is.'</speech> Lao Dan replied, <speech
                    speaker="Laodan">'<positive>In the governing of the intelligent kings, their
                        services overspread all under the sky, but they did not seem to consider it
                        as proceeding from themselves; their transforming influence reached to all
                        things, but the people did not refer it to them with hope. No one could tell
                        the name of their agency, but they made men and things be joyful in
                        themselves. Where they took their stand could not be fathomed, and they
                        found their enjoyment in (the realm of) nonentity.'</positive></speech></p>
        </section>
        <section n="5" type="parable">
            <p>In Zheng there was a mysterious wizard called Ji-xian. He knew all about the deaths
                and births of men, their preservation and ruin, their misery and happiness, and
                whether their lives would be long or short, foretelling the year, the month, the
                decade and the day like a spirit. When the people of Kang saw him, they all ran out
                of his way. Liezi went to see him, and was fascinated by him. Returning, he told
                Hu-zi of his interview, and said, <speech speaker="Liezi">'I considered your
                    doctrine, my master, to be perfect, but I have found another which is superior
                    to it.'</speech> Hu-zi replied, <speech speaker="Huzi">'I have communicated to
                    you but the outward letter of my doctrine, and have not communicated its reality
                    and spirit; and do you think that you are in possession of it? However many hens
                    there be, if there be not the cock among them, how should they lay (real) eggs?
                    When you confront the world with your doctrine, you are sure to show in your
                    countenance (all that is in your mind), and so enable (this) man to succeed in
                    interpreting your physiognomy. Try and come to me with him, that I may show
                    myself to him.'</speech> On the morrow, accordingly, Liezi came with the man and
                saw Hu-zi. When they went out, the wizard said, <speech speaker="Ji-xian">'Alas!
                    your master is a dead man. He will not live;-- not for ten days more! I saw
                    something strange about him - I saw the ashes (of his life) all slaked with
                    water!'</speech> When Liezi reentered, he wept till the front of his jacket was
                wet with his tears, and told Hu-zi what the man had said.</p>
            <p>Hu-zi said, <speech speaker="Huzi">'I showed myself to him with the forms of
                    (vegetation beneath) the earth. There were the sprouts indeed, but without (any
                    appearance of) growth or regularity:-- he seemed to see me with the springs of
                    my (vital) power closed up. Try and come to me with him again.'</speech> Next
                day, accordingly, Liezi brought the man again and saw Hu-zi. When they went out, the
                man said, <speech speaker="the wizard">'It is a fortunate thing for your master that
                    he met with me. He will get better; he has all the signs of living! I saw the
                    balance (of the springs of life) that had been stopped (inclining in his
                    favour).'</speech> Liezi went in, and reported these words to his master, who
                said, <speech speaker="Huzi">'I showed myself to him after the pattern of the earth
                    (beneath the) sky. Neither semblance nor reality entered (into my exhibition),
                    but the springs (of life) were issuing from beneath my feet;-- he seemed to see
                    me with the springs of vigorous action in full play. Try and come with him
                    again.'</speech> Next day Liezi came with the man again, and again saw Hu-zi
                with him. When they went out, the wizard said, <speech speaker="Ji-xian">'Your
                    master is never the same. I cannot understand his physiognomy. Let him try to
                    steady himself, and I will again view him.'</speech> Liezi went in and reported
                this to Hu-zi, who said, <speech speaker="Huzi">'This time I showed myself to him
                    after the pattern of the grand harmony (of the two elemental forces), with the
                    superiority inclining to neither. He seemed to see me with the springs of
                    (vital) power in equal balance. Where the water wheels about from (the movements
                    of) a dugong, there is an abyss; where it does so from the arresting (of its
                    course), there is an abyss; where it does so, and the water keeps flowing on,
                    there is an abyss. There are nine abysses with their several names, and I have
                    only exhibited three of them. Try and come with him again.'</speech> Next day
                they came, and they again saw Hu-zi. But before he had settled himself in his
                position, the wizard lost himself and ran away. <speech speaker="Huzi">'Pursue
                    him,'</speech> said Hu-zi, and Liezi did so, but could not come up with him. He
                returned, and told Hu-zi, saying, <speech speaker="Liezi">'There is an end of him;
                    he is lost; I could not find him.'</speech></p>
            <p>Hu-zi rejoined, <speech speaker="Huzi">'I was showing him myself after the pattern of
                    what was before I began to come from my author. I confronted him with pure
                    vacancy, and an easy indifference. He did not know what I meant to represent.
                    Now he thought it was the idea of exhausted strength, and now that of an onward
                    flow, and therefore he ran away.'</speech> After this, Liezi considered that he
                had not yet begun to learn (his master's doctrine). He returned to his house, and
                for three years did not go out. He did the cooking for his wife. He fed the pigs as
                if he were feeding men. He took no part or interest in occurring affairs. He put
                away the carving and sculpture about him, and returned to pure simplicity. Like a
                clod of earth he stood there in his bodily presence. Amid all distractions he was
                (silent) and shut up in himself. And in this way he continued to the end of his
                life.</p>
        </section>
        <section n="6" type="argument">
            <p><comparison topic="non-action">Non-action (makes its exemplifier) the lord of all
                    fame; non-action (serves him as) the treasury of all plans; non-action (fits him
                    for) the burden of all offices; non-action (makes him) the lord of all wisdom.
                    The range of his action is inexhaustible, but there is nowhere any trace of his
                    presence. He fulfils all that he has received from Heaven, but he does not see
                    that he was the recipient of anything. A pure vacancy (of all purpose) is what
                    characterises him. When the perfect man employs his mind, it is a
                    mirror.</comparison> It conducts nothing and anticipates nothing; it responds to
                (what is before it), but does not retain it. Thus he is able to deal successfully
                with all things, and injures none.</p>
        </section>
        <section n="7" type="parable">
            <p>The Ruler of the Southern Ocean was Shu, the Ruler of the Northern Ocean was Hu, and
                the Ruler of the Centre was Chaos. Shu and Hu were continually meeting in the land
                of Chaos, who treated them very well. They consulted together how they might repay
                his kindness, and said, <speech speaker="Shu and Hu">'Men all have seven orifices
                    for the purpose of seeing, hearing, eating, and breathing, while this (poor)
                    Ruler alone has not one. Let us try and make them for him.' Accordingly they dug
                    one orifice in him every day; and at the end of seven days Chaos
                died.</speech></p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</chapters>
