<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter n="V" name="The Seal of Virtue Complete">
    <section type="parable" n="I">
        <p>In Lu there was a Wang Tai who had lost both his feet; while his disciples who followed
            and went about with him were as numerous as those of Zhongni. Chang Ji asked Zhongni
            about him, saying, <speech speaker="Chang Ji">'Though Wang Tai is a cripple, the
                disciples who follow him about divide Lu equally with you, Master. When he stands,
                he does not teach them; when he sits, he does not discourse to them. But they go to
                him empty, and come back full. Is there indeed such a thing as instruction without
                words? and while the body is imperfect, may the mind be complete? What sort of man
                is he?'</speech> Zhongni replied, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'This master is a sage.
                I have only been too late in going to him. I will make him my teacher; and how much
                more should those do so who are not equal to me! Why should only the state of Lu
                follow him? I will lead on all under heaven with me to do so.'</speech></p>
        <p> Chang Ji rejoined, <speech speaker="Chang Ji">'He is a man who has lost his feet, and
                yet he is known as the venerable Wang - he must be very different from ordinary men.
                What is the peculiar way in which he employs his mind?'</speech> The reply was,
                <speech speaker="Zhongni">'Death and life are great considerations, but they could
                work no change in him. Though heaven and earth were to be overturned and fall, they
                would occasion him no loss. His judgment is fixed regarding that in which there is
                no element of falsehood; and, while other things change, he changes not. The
                transformations of things are to him the developments prescribed for them, and he
                keeps fast hold of the author of them.'</speech></p>
        <p>Chang Ji said, <speech speaker="Chang Ji">'What do you mean?'</speech>
            <speech speaker="Zhongni">'When we look at things,'</speech> said Zhongni, <speech
                speaker="Zhongni">'as they differ, we see them to be different, (as for instance)
                the liver and the gall, or Chu and Yue; when we look at them, as they agree, we see
                them all to be a unity. So it is with this (Wang Tai). He takes no knowledge of the
                things for which his ears and eyes are the appropriate organs, but his mind delights
                itself in the harmony of (all excellent) qualities. He looks at the unity which
                belongs to things, and does not perceive where they have suffered loss. He looks on
                the loss of his feet as only the loss of so much earth.'</speech></p>
        <p>Chang Ji said, <speech speaker="Chang Ji">'He is entirely occupied with his (proper)
                self. By his knowledge he has discovered (the nature of) his mind, and to that he
                holds as what is unchangeable; but how is it that men make so much of him?'</speech>
            The reply was, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'Men do not look into running water as a
                mirror, but into still water - it is only the still water that can arrest them all,
                and keep them (in the contemplation of their real selves). Of things which are what
                they are by the influence of the earth, it is only the pine and cypress which are
                the best instances - in winter as in summer brightly green. Of those which were what
                they were by the influence of Heaven, the most correct examples were Yao and Shun;
                fortunate in (thus) maintaining their own life correct, and so as to correct the
                lives of others. As a verification of the (power of) the original endowment, when it
                has been preserved, take the result of fearlessness - how the heroic spirit of a
                single brave soldier has been thrown into an army of nine hosts. If a man only
                seeking for fame and able in this way to secure it can produce such an effect, how
                much more (may we look for a greater result) from one whose rule is over heaven and
                earth, and holds all things in his treasury, who simply has his lodging in the six
                members of his body, whom his ears and eyes serve but as conveying emblematic images
                of things, who comprehends all his knowledge in a unity, and whose mind never dies!
                If such a man were to choose a day on which he would ascend far on high, men would
                (seek to) follow him there. But how should he be willing to occupy himself with
                other men?'</speech>
        </p>
    </section>
    <section n="II" type="parable">
        <p>Shen-tu Jia was (another) man who had lost his feet. Along with Zi-chan of Zheng he
            studied under the master Bo-hun Wu-ren. Zi-chan said to him (one day), <speech
                speaker="Zi-chan">'If I go out first, do you remain behind; and if you go out first,
                I will remain behind.'</speech> Next day they were again sitting together on the
            same mat in the hall, when Zi-chan said (again), <speech speaker="Zi-Chan">'If I go out
                first, do you remain behind; and if you go out first, I will remain behind. Now I am
                about to go out; will you stay behind or not? Moreover, when you see one of official
                rank (like myself), you do not try to get out of his way - do you consider yourself
                equal to one of official rank?'</speech> Shen-tu Jia replied, <speech
                speaker="Shen-tu Jia">'In our Master's school is there indeed such recognition
                required of official rank? You are one, Sir, whose pleasure is in your official
                rank, and would therefore take precedence of other men. I have heard that when a
                mirror is bright, the dust does not rest on it; when dust rests on it the mirror is
                not bright. When one dwells long with a man of ability and virtue, he comes to be
                without error. There now is our teacher whom you have chosen to make you greater
                than you are; and when you still talk in this way, are you not in error?'</speech>
            Zi-chan rejoined, <speech speaker="Zi-chan">'A (shattered) object as you are, you would
                still strive to make yourself out as good as Yao! If I may form an estimate of your
                virtue, might it not be sufficient to lead you to the examination of
                yourself?'</speech> The other said, <speech speaker="Shen-tu Jia">'Most criminals,
                in describing their offences, would make it out that they ought not to have lost
                (their feet) for them; few would describe them so as to make it appear that they
                should not have preserved their feet. They are only the virtuous who know that such
                a calamity was unavoidable, and therefore rest in it as what was appointed for them.
                When men stand before (an archer like) Yi with his bent bow, if they are in the
                middle of his field, that is the place where they should be hit; and if they be not
                hit, that also was appointed. There are many with their feet entire who laugh at me
                because I have lost my feet, which makes me feel vexed and angry. But when I go to
                our teacher, I throw off that feeling, and return (to a better mood) - he has
                washed, without my knowing it, the other from me by (his instructions in) what is
                good. I have attended him now for nineteen years, and have not known that I am
                without my feet. Now, you, Sir, and I have for the object of our study the (virtue)
                which is internal, and not an adjunct of the body, and yet you are continually
                directing your attention to my external body - are you not wrong in this?'</speech>
            Zi-chan felt uneasy, altered his manner and looks, and said, <speech
                speaker="Shen-tu Jia">'You need not, Sir, say anything more about it.'</speech></p>
    </section>
    <section n="III" type="parable">
        <p>In Lu there was a cripple, called Shu-shan the Toeless, who came on his heels to see
            Zhongni. Zhongni said to him, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'By your want of circumspection
                in the past, Sir, you have incurred such a calamity; of what use is your coming to
                me now?'</speech> Toeless said, <speech speaker="Toeless">'Through my ignorance of
                my proper business and taking too little care of my body, I came to lose my feet.
                But now I am come to you, still possessing what is more honourable than my feet, and
                which therefore I am anxious to preserve entire. There is nothing which Heaven does
                not cover, and nothing which Earth does not sustain; you, Master, were regarded by
                me as doing the part of Heaven and Earth - how could I know that you would receive
                me in such a way?'</speech> Confucius rejoined, <speech speaker="Confucius">'I am
                but a poor creature. But why, my master, do you not come inside, where I will try to
                tell you what I have learned?'</speech> When Toeless had gone out, Confucius said,
                <speech speaker="Confucius">'Be stimulated to effort, my disciples. This toeless
                cripple is still anxious to learn to make up for the evil of his former conduct;--
                how much more should those be so whose conduct has been unchallenged!'</speech> Mr.
            Toeless, however, told Lao Dan (of the interview), saying, <speech speaker="Toeless"
                >'Kong Qiu, I apprehend, has not yet attained to be a Perfect man. What has he to do
                with keeping a crowd of disciples around him? He is seeking to have the reputation
                of being an extraordinary and marvellous man, and does not know that the Perfect man
                considers this to be as handcuffs and fetters to him.'</speech> Lao Dan said,
                <speech speaker="Lao Dan">'Why did you not simply lead him to see the unity of life
                and death, and that the admissible and inadmissible belong to one category, so
                freeing him from his fetters? Would this be possible?'</speech> Toeless said,
                <speech speaker="Toeless">'It is the punishment inflicted on him by Heaven. How can
                he be freed from it?'</speech>
        </p>
    </section>
    <section n="IV" type="parable">
        <p>Duke Ai of Lu asked Zhongni, saying, <speech speaker="Duke Ai">'There was an ugly man in
                Wei, called Ai-tai Tuo. His father-in-law, who lived with him, thought so much of
                him that he could not be away from him. His wife, when she saw him (ugly as he was),
                represented to her parents, saying, "I had more than ten times rather be his
                concubine than the wife of any other man." He was never heard to take the lead in
                discussion, but always seemed to be of the same opinion with others. He had not the
                position of a ruler, so as to be able to save men from death. He had no revenues, so
                as to be able to satisfy men's craving for food. He was ugly enough, moreover, to
                scare the whole world. He agreed with men instead of trying to lead them to adopt
                his views; his knowledge did not go beyond his immediate neighbourhood. And yet his
                father-in-law and his wife were of one mind about him in his presence (as I have
                said) - he must have been different from other men. I called him, and saw him.
                Certainly he was ugly enough to scare the whole world. He had not lived with me,
                however, for many months, when I was drawn to the man; and before he had been with
                me a full year, I had confidence in him. The state being without a chief minister, I
                (was minded) to commit the government to him. He responded to my proposal
                sorrowfully, and looked undecided as if he would fain have declined it. I was
                ashamed of myself (as inferior to him), but finally gave the government into his
                hands. In a little time, however, he left me and went away. I was sorry and felt
                that I had sustained a loss, and as if there were no other to share the pleasures of
                the kingdom with me. What sort of man was he?'</speech></p>
        <p> Zhongni said, <speech speaker="Zhongni">'Once when I was sent on a mission to Qi, I saw
                some pigs sucking at their dead mother. After a little they looked with rapid
                glances, when they all left her, and ran away. They felt that she did not see them,
                and that she was no longer like themselves. What they had loved in their mother was
                not her bodily figure, but what had given animation to her figure. When a man dies
                in battle, they do not at his interment employ the usual appendages of plumes: as to
                supplying shoes to one who has lost his feet, there is no reason why he should care
                for them - in neither case is there the proper reason for their use. The members of
                the royal harem do not pare their nails nor pierce their ears; when a man is newly
                married, he remains (for a time) absent from his official duties, and unoccupied
                with them. That their bodies might be perfect was sufficient to make them thus dealt
                with; how much greater results should be expected from men whose mental gifts are
                perfect! This Ai-tai Tuo was believed by men, though he did not speak a word; and
                was loved by them, though he did no special service for them. He made men appoint
                him to the government of their states, afraid only that he would not accept the
                appointment. He must have been a man whose powers were perfect, though his
                realisation of them was not manifested in his person.</speech></p>
        <p> Duke Ai said, <speech speaker="Duke Ai">'What is meant by saying that his powers were
                complete?' Zhongni replied, 'Death and life, preservation and ruin, failure and
                success, poverty and wealth, superiority and inferiority, blame and praise, hunger
                and thirst, cold and heat; these are the changes of circumstances, the operation of
                our appointed lot. Day and night they succeed to one another before us, but there is
                no wisdom able to discover to what they owe their origination. They are not
                sufficient therefore to disturb the harmony (of the nature), and are not allowed to
                enter into the treasury of intelligence. To cause this harmony and satisfaction ever
                to be diffused, while the feeling of pleasure is not lost from the mind; to allow no
                break to arise in this state day or night, so that it is always spring-time in his
                relations with external things; in all his experiences to realise in his mind what
                is appropriate to each season (of the year): these are the characteristics of him
                whose powers are perfect.'</speech></p>
        <p><speech speaker="Duke Ai"> 'And what do you mean by the realisation of these powers not
                being manifested in the person?'</speech> (pursued further the duke). The reply was,
                <speech speaker="Zhongni">'There is nothing so level as the surface of a pool of
                still water. It may serve as an example of what I mean. All within its circuit is
                preserved (in peace), and there comes to it no agitation from without. The virtuous
                efficacy is the perfect cultivation of the harmony (of the nature). Though the
                realisation of this be not manifested in the person, things cannot separate
                themselves (from its influence).'</speech></p>
        <p> Some days afterwards duke Ai told this conversation to Min-zi, saying, <speech
                speaker="Duke Ai">'Formerly it seemed to me the work of the sovereign to stand in
                court with his face to the south, to rule the kingdom, and to pay good heed to the
                accounts of the people concerned, lest any should come to a (miserable) death - this
                I considered to be the sum (of his duty). Now that I have heard that description of
                the Perfect man, I fear that my idea is not the real one, and that, by employing
                myself too lightly, I may cause the ruin of my state. I and Kong Qiu are not on the
                footing of ruler and subject, but on that of a virtuous friendship.'</speech></p>
    </section>
    <section n="V" type="parable">
        <p>A person who had no lips, whose legs were bent so that he could only walk on his toes,
            and who was (otherwise) deformed, addressed his counsels to duke Ling of Wei, who was so
            pleased with him, that he looked on a perfectly formed man as having a lean and small
            neck in comparison with him. Another who had a large goitre like an earthenware jar
            addressed his counsels to duke Huan of Qi, who was so pleased with him that he looked on
            a perfectly formed man as having a neck lean and small in comparison with him. So it is
            that when one's virtue is extraordinary, (any deficiency in) his bodily form may be
            forgotten. When men do not forget what is (easily) forgotten, and forget what is not
            (easily) forgotten, we have a case of real oblivion. Therefore the sagely man has that
            in which his mind finds its enjoyment, and (looks on) wisdom as (but) the shoots from an
            old stump; agreements with others are to him but so much glue; kindnesses are (but the
            arts of) intercourse; and great skill is (but as) merchants' wares. The sagely man lays
            no plans; of what use would wisdom be to him? He has no cutting and hacking to do; of
            what use would glue be to him? He has lost nothing; of what use would arts of
            intercourse be to him? He has no goods to dispose of; what need has he to play the
            merchant? (The want of) these four things are the nourishment of (his) Heavenly
            (nature); that nourishment is its Heavenly food. Since he receives this food from
            Heaven, what need has he for anything of man's (devising)? He has the bodily form of
            man, but not the passions and desires of (other) men. He has the form of man, and
            therefore he is a man. Being without the passions and desires of men, their approvings
            and disapprovings are not to be found in him. How insignificant and small is (the body)
            by which he belongs to humanity! How grand and great is he in the unique perfection of
            his Heavenly (nature)!</p>
    </section>
    <section n="VI" type="parable">
        <p>Huizi said to Zhuangzi, <speech speaker="Huizi">'Can a man indeed be without desires and
                passions?'</speech> The reply was, <speech speaker="Zhuangzi">'He can.'
                </speech><speech speaker="Huizi">'But on what grounds do you call him a man, who is
                thus without passions and desires?'</speech> Zhuangzi said, <speech
                speaker="Zhuangzi">'The Dao gives him his personal appearance (and powers); Heaven
                gives him his bodily form; how should we not call him a man?'</speech> Huizi
            rejoined, <speech speaker="Huizi"> 'Since you call him a man, how can he be without
                passions and desires?'</speech> The reply was, <speech speaker="Zhuangzi">'You are
                misunderstanding what I mean by passions and desires. What I mean when I say that he
                is without these is, that this man does not by his likings and dislikings do any
                inward harm to his body - he always pursues his course without effort, and does not
                (try to) increase his (store of) life.'</speech> Huizi rejoined, <speech
                speaker="Huizi">'If there were not that increasing of (the amount) of life, how
                would he get his body?'</speech> Zhuangzi said, <speech speaker="Zhuangzi">'The Dao
                gives him his personal appearance (and powers); Heaven gives him his bodily form;
                and he does not by his likings and dislikings do any internal harm to his body. But
                now you, Sir, deal with your spirit as if it were something external to you, and
                subject your vital powers to toil. You sing (your ditties), leaning against a tree;
                you go to sleep, grasping the stump of a rotten dryandra tree. Heaven selected for
                you the bodily form (of a man), and you babble about what is strong and what is
                white.'</speech></p>
    </section>
</chapter>
