<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter n="3" name="Nourishing the Lord of Life">
    <section n="1" type="argument">
        <p>There is a limit to our life, but to knowledge there is no limit. With what is limited to
            pursue after what is unlimited is a perilous thing; and when, knowing this, we still
            seek the increase of our knowledge, the peril cannot be averted. There should not be the
            practice of what is good with any thought of the fame (which it will bring), nor of what
            is evil with any approximation to the punishment (which it will incur): an accordance
            with the Central Element (of our nature) is the regular way to preserve the body, to
            maintain the life, to nourish our parents, and to complete our term of years. </p>
    </section>
    <section n="2" type="parable">
        <p>His cook was cutting up an ox for the ruler Wen Hui. Whenever he applied his hand, leaned
            forward with his shoulder, planted his foot, and employed the pressure of his knee, in
            the audible ripping off of the skin, and slicing operation of the knife, the sounds were
            all in regular cadence. <figurative style="simile">Movements and sounds proceeded as in the dance of 'the Mulberry
            Forest' and the blended notes of the King Shou.'</figurative> The ruler said, <speech
                speaker="King Shou">'Ah! Admirable! That your art should have become so
                perfect!'</speech> (Having finished his operation), the cook laid down his knife,
            and replied to the remark, <speech speaker="Cook">'What your servant loves is the method
                of the Dao, something in advance of any art. When I first began to cut up an ox, I
                saw nothing but the (entire) carcase. After three years I ceased to see it as a
                whole. Now I deal with it in a spirit-like manner, and <figurative style="metaphor">do not look at it with my
                eyes.</figurative> The use of my senses is discarded, and my spirit acts as it wills. Observing
                the natural lines, (my knife) <figurative style="personification">slips through the great crevices and slides through
                the great cavities, taking advantage of the facilities thus presented.</figurative> My art avoids
                the membranous ligatures, and much more the great bones. A good cook changes his
                knife every year; (it may have been injured) in cutting - an ordinary cook changes
                his every month - (it may have been) broken. Now my knife has been in use for
                nineteen years; it has cut up several thousand oxen, and yet its edge is as sharp as
                if it had newly come from the whetstone. There are the interstices of the joints,
                and the edge of the knife has no (appreciable) thickness; when that which is so thin
                enters where the interstice is, how easily it moves along! The blade has more than
                room enough. Nevertheless, whenever I come to a complicated joint, and see that
                there will be some difficulty, I proceed anxiously and with caution, not allowing my
                eyes to wander from the place, and moving my hand slowly. Then by a very slight
                movement of the knife, the part is quickly separated, and <figurative style="simile">drops like (a clod of)
                earth to the ground</figurative>. Then standing up with the knife in my hand, I look all round,
                and in a leisurely manner, with an air of satisfaction, wipe it clean, and put it in
                its sheath.'</speech> The ruler Wen Hui said, <speech speaker="Wen Hui">'Excellent!
                I have heard the words of my cook, and learned from them the nourishment of (our)
                life.'</speech></p>
    </section>
    <section n="3" type="parable">
        <p>When Gong-wen Xian saw the Master of the Left, he was startled, and said, <speech
                speaker="Gong-Wen Xian">'What sort of man is this? How is it he has but one foot? Is
                it from Heaven? or from Man?'</speech> Then he added, <speech
                speaker="Gong-Wen Xian">'It must be from Heaven, and not from Man. Heaven's making
                of this man caused him to have but one foot. In the person of man, each foot has its
                marrow. By this I know that his peculiarity is from Heaven, and not from
                Man.</speech></p>
    </section>
    <section n="4" type="parable">
        <p>A pheasant of the marshes has to take ten steps to pick up a mouthful of food, and thirty
            steps to get a drink, but it does not seek to be nourished in a coop. Though its spirit
            would (there) enjoy a royal abundance, it does not think (such confinement) good.' </p>
    </section>
    <section n="5" type="parable">
        <p>When Lao Dan died, Qin Shi went to console (with his son), but after crying out three
            times, he came out. The disciples said to him, <speech speaker="Disciples">'Were you not
                a friend of the Master?'</speech>
            <speech speaker="Qin Shi">'I was,'</speech> he replied, and they said, <speech
                speaker="Disciples">'Is it proper then to offer your condolences merely as you have
                done?'</speech> He said,<speech speaker="Qin Shi"> 'It is. At first I thought he was
                the man of men, and now I do not think so. When I entered a little ago and expressed
                my condolences, there were the <comparison topic="mourning">old men wailing as if they had lost a son</comparison>, and the
                <comparison topic="mourning">young men wailing as if they had lost their mother</comparison>. In his attracting and uniting
                them to himself in such a way there must have been that which made them
                involuntarily express their words (of condolence), and involuntarily wail, as they
                were doing. And this was a hiding from himself of his Heaven (-nature), and an
                excessive indulgence of his (human) feelings; a forgetting of what he had received
                (in being born); what the ancients called the punishment due to neglecting the
                Heaven (-nature). When the Master came, it was at the proper time; when he went
                away, it was the simple sequence (of his coming). Quiet acquiescence in what happens
                at its proper time, and quietly submitting (to its ceasing) afford no occasion for
                grief or for joy. <ref kind="indirect-quote">The ancients described (death) as the loosening of the cord on
                which God suspended (the life).</ref></speech>
        </p>
    </section>
    <section n="6" type="argument">
        <p>What we can point to are the faggots that have been consumed; but the fire is transmitted
            (elsewhere), and we know not that it is over and ended.</p>
    </section>
</chapter>
