<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<collection>
    <doctrine>
        <line number="1-5">The Master said, "To rule a country of a thousand chariots, there must be
            reverent attention to business, and sincerity; economy in expenditure, and love for men;
            and the employment of the people at the proper seasons." </line>
        <line number="1-10">Zi Qin asked Zi Gong, saying, "When our master comes to any country, he
            does not fail to learn all about its government. Does he ask his information? or is it
            given to him?" Zi Gong said, "Our master is benign, upright, courteous, temperate, and
            complaisant and thus he gets his information. The master's mode of asking information! -
            is it not different from that of other men?"</line>
        <line number="1-14">The Master said, "He who aims to be a man of complete virtue in his food
            does not seek to gratify his appetite, nor in his dwelling place does he seek the
            appliances of ease; he is earnest in what he is doing, and careful in his speech; he
            frequents the company of men of principle that he may be rectified - such a person may
            be said indeed to love to learn."</line>
        <line number="2-1">The Master said, "He who exercises government by means of his virtue may
            be compared to the north polar star, which keeps its place and all the stars turn
            towards it."</line>
        <line number="2-3">The Master said, "If the people be led by laws, and uniformity sought to
            be given them by punishments, they will try to avoid the punishment, but have no sense
            of shame. If they be led by virtue, and uniformity sought to be given them by the rules
            of propriety, they will have the sense of shame, and moreover will become good."</line>
        <line number="2-19">The Duke Ai asked, saying, "What should be done in order to secure the
            submission of the people?" Confucius replied, "Advance the upright and set aside the
            crooked, then the people will submit. Advance the crooked and set aside the upright,
            then the people will not submit."</line>
        <line number="2-21">Some one addressed Confucius, saying, "Sir, why are you not engaged in
            the government?" The Master said, "What does the Shu Jing say of filial piety? - 'You
            are filial, you discharge your brotherly duties. These qualities are displayed in
            government.' This then also constitutes the exercise of government. Why must there be
            THAT - making one be in the government?"</line>
        <line number="4-15">The Master said, "Shen, my doctrine is that of an all-pervading unity."
            The disciple Zeng replied, "Yes." The Master went out, and the other disciples asked,
            saying, "What do his words mean?" Zeng said, "The doctrine of our master is to be true
            to the principles of our nature and the benevolent exercise of them to others, this and
            nothing more."</line>
        <line number="4-26">Zi You said, "In serving a prince, frequent remonstrances lead to
            disgrace. Between friends, frequent reproofs make the friendship distant."</line>
        <line number="6-18">The Master said, "Where the solid qualities are in excess of
            accomplishments, we have rusticity; where the accomplishments are in excess of the solid
            qualities, we have the manners of a clerk. When the accomplishments and solid qualities
            are equally blended, we then have the man of virtue."</line>
        <line number="14-3"> The Master said, "When good government prevails in a state, language
            may be lofty and bold, and actions the same. When bad government prevails, the actions
            may be lofty and bold, but the language may be with some reserve."</line>
        <line number="15-5">The Master said, "When good government prevails in a state, language may
            be lofty and bold, and actions the same. When bad government prevails, the actions may
            be lofty and bold, but the language may be with some reserve."</line>
    </doctrine>
    <zhongni>
        <line number="7-1">The Master said, "A transmitter and not a maker, believing in and loving
            the ancients, I venture to compare myself with our old Peng."</line>
        <line number="7-2">The Master said, "The silent treasuring up of knowledge; learning without
            satiety; and instructing others without being wearied - which one of these things
            belongs to me?"</line>
        <line number="7-4">When the Master was unoccupied with business, his manner was easy, and he
            looked pleased.</line>
        <line number="7-5">The Master said, "Extreme is my decay. For a long time, I have not
            dreamed, as I was wont to do, that I saw the duke of Zhou."</line>
        <line number="7-16">The Master said, "With coarse rice to eat, with water to drink, and my
            bended arm for a pillow; I have still joy in the midst of these things. Riches and
            honors acquired by unrighteousness, are to me as a floating cloud."</line>
        <line number="9-1">The subjects of which the Master seldom spoke were: profitableness, and
            also the appointments of Heaven, and perfect virtue.</line>
    </zhongni>
    <Yanyuan>
        <line number="5-26">Yan Yuan and Ji Lu being by his side, the Master said to them, "Come,
            let each of you tell his wishes." Zi Lu said, "I should like, having chariots and
            horses, and light fur clothes, to share them with my friends, and though they should
            spoil them, I would not be displeased." Yan Yuan said, "I should like not to boast of my
            excellence, nor to make a display of my meritorious deeds." Zi Lu then said, "I should
            like, sir, to hear your wishes." The Master said, "They are, in regard to the aged, to
            give them rest; in regard to friends, to show them sincerity; in regard to the young, to
            treat them tenderly."</line>
        <line number="6-3">The Duke Ai asked which of the disciples loved to learn. Confucius
            replied to him, "There was Yan Hui; HE loved to learn. He did not transfer his anger; he
            did not repeat a fault. Unfortunately, his appointed time was short and he died; and now
            there is not such another. I have not yet heard of any one who loves to learn as he
            did."</line>
        <line number="6-7">The Master said, "Such was Hui that for three months there would be
            nothing in his mind contrary to perfect virtue. The others may attain to this on some
            days or in some months, but nothing more."</line>
        <line number="6-11">The Master said, "Admirable indeed was the virtue of Hui! With a single
            bamboo dish of rice, a single gourd dish of drink, and living in his mean narrow lane,
            while others could not have endured the distress, he did not allow his joy to be
            affected by it. Admirable indeed was the virtue of Hui!"</line>
        <line number="9-11">Yan Yuan, in admiration of the Master's doctrines, sighed and said, "I
            looked up to them, and they seemed to become more high; I tried to penetrate them, and
            they seemed to become more firm; I looked at them before me, and suddenly they seemed to
            be behind. The Master, by orderly method, skillfully leads men on. He enlarged my mind
            with learning, and taught me the restraints of propriety. When I wish to give over the
            study of his doctrines, I cannot do so, and having exerted all my ability, there seems
            something to stand right up before me; but though I wish to follow and lay hold of it, I
            really find no way to do so."</line>
        <line number="9-21">The Master said of Yan Yuan, "Alas! I saw his constant advance. I never
            saw him stop in his progress."</line>
        <line number="11-3">Distinguished for their virtuous principles and practice, there were Yan
            Yuan, Min Zi Qian, Ran Bo Niu, and Zhong Gong; for their ability in speech, Zai Wo and
            Zi Gong; for their administrative talents, Ran You and Ji Lu; for their literary
            acquirements, Zi You and Zi Xia.</line>
        <line number="11-4">The Master said, "Hui gives me no assistance. There is nothing that I
            say in which he does not delight."</line>
        <line number="11-8">When Yan Yuan died, Yan Lu begged the carriage of the Master to sell and
            get an outer shell for his son's coffin. The Master said, "Whether he has talents or has
            not talents, everyone calls his son his son. There was Li; when he died, he had a coffin
            but no outer shell. I would not walk on foot to get a shell for him, because, having
            followed in the rear of the great officers, it was not proper that I should walk on
            foot."</line>
        <line number="11-9">When Yan Yuan died, the Master said, "Alas! Heaven is destroying me!
            Heaven is destroying me!"</line>
        <line number="11-10">When Yan Yuan died, the Master bewailed him exceedingly, and the
            disciples who were with him said, "Master, your grief is excessive!" "Is it excessive?"
            said he. "If I am not to mourn bitterly for this man, for whom should I mourn?"</line>
        <line numbere="11-11">When Yan Yuan died, the disciples wished to give him a great funeral,
            and the Master said, "You may not do so." The disciples did bury him in great style. The
            Master said, "Hui behaved towards me as his father. I have not been able to treat him as
            my son. The fault is not mine; it belongs to you, O disciples."</line>
        <line number="11-19">The Master said, "There is Hui! He has nearly attained to perfect
            virtue. He is often in want. Ci does not acquiesce in the appointments of Heaven, and
            his goods are increased by him. Yet his judgments are often correct."</line>
        <line number="11-23">The Master was put in fear in Kuang and Yan Yuan fell behind. The
            Master, on his rejoining him, said, "I thought you had died." Hui replied, "While you
            were alive, how should I presume to die?"</line>
        <line number="12-1">Yan Yuan asked about perfect virtue. The Master said, "To subdue one's
            self and return to propriety, is perfect virtue. If a man can for one day subdue himself
            and return to propriety, all under heaven will ascribe perfect virtue to him. Is the
            practice of perfect virtue from a man himself, or is it from others?" Yan Yuan said, "I
            beg to ask the steps of that process." The Master replied, "Look not at what is contrary
            to propriety; listen not to what is contrary to propriety; speak not what is contrary to
            propriety; make no movement which is contrary to propriety." Yan Yuan then said, "Though
            I am deficient in intelligence and vigor, I will make it my business to practice this
            lesson."</line>
        <line number="15-11">Yan Yuan asked how the government of a country should be administered.
            The Master said, "Follow the seasons of Xia. Ride in the state carriage of Yin. Wear the
            ceremonial cap of Zhou. Let the music be the Shao with its pantomimes. Banish the songs
            of Zheng, and keep far from specious talkers. The songs of Zheng are licentious;
            specious talkers are dangerous."</line>
    </Yanyuan>
    <Jieyu>
        <line number="18-5">The madman of Chu, Jie Yu, passed by Confucius, singing and saying, "O
            Feng! O Feng! How is your virtue degenerated! As to the past, reproof is useless; but
            the future may still be provided against. Give up your vain pursuit. Give up your vain
            pursuit. Peril awaits those who now engage in affairs of government." Confucius alighted
            and wished to converse with him, but Jie Yu hastened away, so that he could not talk
            with him.</line>
    </Jieyu>
</collection>
